<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great and ancient charter of the Cinque-Ports of our lord the King, and the members of the same</title>
            <author>Cinque Ports (Association)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 165 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 71 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41855</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1632</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R215891</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827649</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827649</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32072</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41855)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32072)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1848:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great and ancient charter of the Cinque-Ports of our lord the King, and the members of the same</title>
                  <author>Cinque Ports (Association)</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II). aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>141, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by T.N. for the Mayor and jurats of Hasting,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated on p.122: Witness our Self at Westminster the three and twentieth day of December, in the twentieth year of the reign of Us Charles the Second, &amp;c.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cinque Ports --  Charters --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32072:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32072:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Great and Ancient</hi> CHARTER OF THE Cinque-Ports OF Our LORD the KING, And of The Members of the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>T. N.</hi> for the Mayor and Jurats of <hi>Haſting,</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="charter">
            <pb facs="tcp:32072:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:32072:2"/>
            <head>The Great and Ancient CHARTER OF THE Cinque-Ports.</head>
            <div n="3-50" type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Second,<note place="margin">Char. 2.</note> By the Grace of God, of <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> King, Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To all thoſe to whom theſe Our preſent Letters-Patents ſhall come, Greeting. We have look'd over the Letters-Patents of Our famous Predeceſſor the Lady <hi>Eliz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abeth</hi> late Queen of <hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eliz.</note> about Confirmation, according to theſe words, viz. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> by the Grace of God, of <hi>England, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Queen, Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To all thoſe to whom theſe preſent Letters-Patents ſhall come, Greeting. We have look'd
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32072:3"/> over the Letters-Patents of the Lady <hi>Mary,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mar.</note> late Queen of <hi>England,</hi> Our dearly beloved Siſter, about Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, made according to theſe words: <hi>Mary,</hi> by the Grace of God, of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Queen, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the Faith, and upon Earth of the Church of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Supream Head, To all thoſe to whom our preſent Letters-Patents ſhall come, Greeting. We have look'd upon the Letters-Patents of <hi>Edward</hi> VI. Lord,<note place="margin">Edw. 6.</note> late King of <hi>England,</hi> Our Brother, about Confirmation, made according to theſe words: <hi>Edward</hi> VI. by the Grace of God, of <hi>England, France,</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> King, Defender of the Faith, and upon Earth of the Church of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> Supream Head, To all thoſe to whom Our preſent Letters-Patents ſhall come, Greeting. We have look'd upon the Letters-Patents of <hi>Henry</hi> VIII Lord,<note place="margin">Hen. 8.</note> late King of <hi>England,</hi> Our mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dear Father, about Confirmation, made according to theſe words, <hi>Henry,</hi> by the Grace of God, King of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> and Lord of <hi>Ireland,</hi> To all thoſe to whom theſe preſent Letters-Patents ſhall come, Greeting. We have look'd upon the Letters-Patents
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:32072:3"/> of <hi>Henry,</hi> Lord,<note place="margin">Hen. 7.</note> late King of <hi>England,</hi> Our Father, about Confirmation, made according to theſe words: <hi>Henry,</hi> by the Grace of God, King of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> and Lord of <hi>Ireland,</hi> To all thoſe to whom theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Letters ſhall come, Greeting. We have look'd upon the Charter of <hi>Edward</hi> IV. Lord, late King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> made ſince the Conqueſt, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to theſe words: <hi>Edward,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Edw. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> by the Grace of God, King of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> and Lord of <hi>Ireland,</hi> To the Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Abbots, Priors, Dukes, Earls, Barons, Juſtices, She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs, Chief Officers, and to all Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffs and faithful Subjects, Greeting. We have look'd upon the Charter of Confirmation of <hi>Richard</hi> II. Lord, late King of <hi>England,</hi> ſince the Conqueſt, made according to theſe words: <hi>Richard,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rich. 2.</note> by the Grace of God, King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> and Lord of <hi>Ireland,</hi> To all thoſe to whom Our preſent Letters ſhall come, Greeting. We have look'd upon the Charter of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of <hi>Edward,</hi> Lord, late King of <hi>England</hi> Our Grandfather, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to theſe words: <hi>Edward,</hi> by the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32072:4"/> Grace of God, King of <hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Edw. 3.</note> Lord of <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Aquitain,</hi> To the Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Abbots, Priors, Dukes, Earls, Barons Juſtices, Sheriffs, Head-Officers, and to all Bailiffs and faithful Subjects, Greeting. We have look'd upon the Charter of <hi>Edward,</hi> Lord, late King of <hi>England,</hi> Our Father, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to theſe words: <hi>Edward,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Edw. 2.</note> by the Grace of God, King of <hi>England,</hi> Lord of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Duke of <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> To Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bots, Priors, Dukes, Earls, Barons, Juſtices, Sheriffs, Head-Officers, and to all Bailiffs, and faithful Subjects, Greet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. We have look'd upon the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which <hi>Edward,</hi> Lord, late King of <hi>England,</hi> Our Father, granted to the Barons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to theſe words: <hi>Edward,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Edw. 1.</note> by the Grace of God, King of <hi>England,</hi> Lord of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Duke of <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> To the Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Abbots, Priors, Earls, Barons, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices, Sheriffs, Head-Officers, and to all Bailiffs, and faithful Subjects, Greeting. Know ye, that for the faithful Service which Our Barons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> have hitherto paid to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:32072:4"/> Our Predeceſſors the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> and to Us lately in Our Army in <hi>Wales,</hi> and for their good Service to be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued for the future faithfully to Us and to Our Heirs the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> We have granted and confirmed by this Our Charter for Us and Our Heirs to the ſame Our Barons, and their Heirs, all their Liberties and Acquitances,<note place="margin">The Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </note> ſo that they may be free from all Toll, and from all Cuſtom, <hi>viz.</hi> from all Laſtage, Tallage, Paſſage, Carriage, Riverage, Bridg-toll, and all Wreck, and from all Sale, as their Achat and Reachat through Our whole Land and Dominion, with Soc and Sac, Thol and Them, and that they may have In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fangtheff, and be Wreckfree, and Witt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>free, Laſtage-free, and * Lovecope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>free, and that they may have Den and Strond at <hi>Great Yarmouth,</hi> according to what is contained in an Ordinance by Us thereupon made, and for ever to be obſerved; and alſo that they be quit from Cuſtoms to be done to Shires and Hundreds; ſo that if any one brings an Action againſt them, they ſhall not Anſwer nor Defend themſelves other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than they uſed to do in the time of <hi>Henry,</hi> Lord, Our Great Grandfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32072:5"/> as alſo that they may have what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they find by Sea and Land, and that they be quit as to all their Goods and Merchandiſing, as Our Free-men; and that they have their due Reſpects at Our Court, and their Liberties through Our Dominions whereſoever they ſhall come; and that in all their Lands which they were poſſeſſed of in the time of the Lord <hi>Henry,</hi> Our Father, <hi>viz.</hi> in the Forty fourth year of his Reign, they be quit for ever from the General Summons before Our Itinerate Juſtices, at what Pleas ſoever, in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Counties their ſaid Lands be, as alſo they ſhall not be bound to appear before Our Juſtices aforeſaid, unleſs any of the Barons ſue any Man, or be ſued by any. And that they ſhall not be Impleaded but where they ought, and are wont to be, <hi>viz.</hi> at <hi>Shepwey;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Shepwey.</note> And that for the reſt of their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Acquitances, they have them as well, fully and honorably, as they and their Predeceſſors had them here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore by their Charters in the times of the Kings of <hi>England, Edward, William the Firſt and the Second,</hi> King <hi>Henry</hi> Our Great-Grandfather, and of <hi>Henry</hi> Lord the King Our Father, as thoſe Charters
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:32072:5"/> which Our ſaid Barons have from thence, and which We have look'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, do reaſonably teſtifie. And We forbid any one to diſturb them or their Trading upon pain of the forfeiture of Ten pounds to Us, provided that if the Barons be defective in doing and taking Juſtice, that the Warden of the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> to Us and Our Heirs for the time being, ſhall enter upon their Ports, and Liberties upon default of the ſaid Barons to do full Juſtice there; Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded always that the ſaid Barons and their Heirs ſhall pay to Us and Our Heirs the Kings of <hi>England</hi> every year, the full Service of Fifty ſeven Ships at their own Coſt, for fifteen days, at the Summons of Us or Our Heirs. We have likewiſe granted to them of Our ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Grace,<note place="margin">Utfang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theff.</note> that they may have Ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fangtheff in their Lands within the Ports aforeſaid, like as Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Abbots, Earls and Barons have in their reſpective Mannors in the County of <hi>Kent:</hi> And that they ſhall not be Impannel'd upon Aſſizes,<note place="margin">Not be Impan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſizes.</note> or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, or any Recognizances by reaſon of their Foreign Tenure againſt their Will: And that of their own Wines in which they Traffick, they ſhall be quit
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:32072:6"/> from Our Right-Price,<note place="margin">Right-Price of Wine.</note> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> of one Pipe of Wine before the Maſt, and another behind the Maſt: And we have fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther granted to the ſaid Barons for Us and Our Heirs, that they ſhall have this Liberty for ever, <hi>viz.</hi> that We or Our Heirs ſhall not have the Guardianſhip, or Giving in Marriage their Heirs upon the account of their Lands which they hold within the Liberties and Ports aforeſaid, for which they pay their aforeſaid Service, and for which We or Our Predeceſſors had not the Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dianſhip,<note place="margin">Giving in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</note> and giving in Marriage in times paſt: But the aforeſaid Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Liberties and Acquaitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces aforeſaid, and other Grants follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, We of Our ſpecial Grace have caus'd to be renew'd to them; Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded always in all things there be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing prejudicial to his Majeſties Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, to Us, and to Our Heirs, or hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the Priviledges of Our Crown, Life, and Members. Wherefore We Will, and firmly Command for Us and Our Heirs, that the Barons aforeſaid for ever enjoy all their Liberties and Acquitances aforeſaid, according as the Charters aforeſaid do reaſonably teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie: And that of Our ſpecial Grace they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32072:6"/> may have Utfangtheff in their reſpective Lands within the Ports aforeſaid,<note place="margin">Utfang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theff.</note> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame manner as Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Abbots, Earls, and Barons have in their reſpective Mannors in the County of <hi>Kent:</hi> And that they ſhall not put in the Aſſizes, Juries, or any Recognizances upon the account of their Forreign Tenure, againſt their Will; And that in their own Wines in which they Traffick, they ſhall be quit from Our Right-Price, <hi>viz.</hi> of one Pipe of Wine before the Maſt, and another be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the Maſt: And that in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner they may for ever enjoy the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty aforeſaid, <hi>viz.</hi> That We or Our Heirs ſhall not have the Guardianſhip or Giving in Marriage their Heirs, upon the account of their Lands which they hold within the Liberties and Ports aforeſaid, for which they pay their aforeſaid Service, and for which We or Our Predeceſſors had the Guardian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or Giving in Marriage in times paſt: But the aforeſaid Confirmation of the Liberties and Acquitances afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and other Our Grants following, We of Our ſpecial Grace have caus'd to be renew'd to them; Provided al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in all things there be nothing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:32072:7"/> to his Majeſties Dignity, to US, and to Our Heirs, or hurtful to the Priviledges of Our Crown, Life, and Members, as aforeſaid, Witneſſes here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto being the Reverend Father <hi>Robert Portunenſis</hi> Biſhop, Cardinal of the Holy See of <hi>Rome,</hi> Frier <hi>William de South,</hi> Provincial Prior of the Fryer Preachers in <hi>England, William de Valentia</hi> our Uncle, <hi>Roger de Mortuo Mari, Roger de Clifford,</hi> Mr. <hi>Walter Stamell</hi> Dean of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> Mr. <hi>Robert Scarborough</hi> Arch-Deacon of the <hi>Eaſt-Ridings,</hi> Mr. <hi>Robert Sexton, Bartholomew de Southley, Thomas de Wayland, Walter de Hopton, Thomas de Normannel, Stephen de Penceſtre, Francis de Bonona, John de Levetot, John de Metingham,</hi> and others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Given under Our Hand at</hi> Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>the Seventeenth day of</hi> June, <hi>in the Sixth Year of Our Reign.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Charter, before the Signing thereof, was by the Kings command openly read in the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſence of the abovenamed Witneſſes and others of Our Council then preſent, and was heard, examined, and agreed upon in the form above-written. We have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32072:7"/> look'd upon the Letters-Patents which the ſame Our Father made to the Barons aforeſaid after theſe words, <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> by the Grace of God, King of <hi>England,</hi> Lord of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Duke of <hi>Aquitain,</hi> To all Bailiffs and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Subjects, to whom theſe preſent Letters ſhall come, Greeting. Know ye, that for the faithful Service which Our Truſty and Well-beloved Barons, and other Our Honeſt Men of the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> have hitherto paid to Us, and Our Progenitors the former Kings of <hi>England,</hi> and ſhall pay for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, We have granted to them for Us and Our Heirs, that they and their Heirs the Barons of the ſaid Ports ſhall for the future be ever free from all Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages<note place="margin">From all Talla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</note> and Subſidies to be paid to Us and Our Heirs out of the whole or any part of their own proper Ships. We have alſo granted to the ſame Barons and Men for us and Our Heirs, That con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the lawful things and Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities which they in due manner ſhall buy within Our Dominion of <hi>Ireland,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </note> no one may be their Partners in thoſe Things and Commodities, nor partake with them in any wiſe againſt the Will of the ſame Barons and Men. We
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:32072:8"/> have further granted for Us, and Our Heirs, as much as in Us lyeth, to the Barons and Truſty Perſons aforeſaid, That all and every of them born with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the aforeſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> although they have Lands or Tenements without the Liberties of the ſaid Ports, which are held by ſuch a Service as the Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in Marriage upon the account of their being under Age,<note place="margin">Giving in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</note> which belongs to Us and Our Heirs, according to the Law and Cuſtom of Our Realm. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, according to the Liberty of the Ports, they may Marry themſelves without the let or impediment of Us or Our Heirs for ever, any Right to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And therefore we charge you, and every of you, that ye moleſt not, or diſturb the Barons and Perſons afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid in any thing contrary to theſe Our Grants. In witneſs whereof we have cauſed theſe Our Letters to be made Patents, Witneſs Our Self at St. <hi>Albans</hi> the Twenty eighth day of <hi>April,</hi> in the Twenty ſixth year of Our Reign.</p>
               <p>We have alſo look'd upon ſome other Letters-Patents which Our ſaid Father granted to the above-named
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:32072:8"/> Barons, after theſe words, <hi>Edward,</hi> by the Grace of God King of <hi>England,</hi> Lord of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Duke of <hi>Aquitain,</hi> To all thoſe to whom theſe preſent Letters ſhall come, Greeting. Taking into conſideration that the Navy of Our <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> cannot be maintained without great Charge and Expences, left the ſaid Navy ſhould fail or decay for the future, We have granted for Us and Our Heirs, That all the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> aforeſaid, and all other Advocants whatſoever that are willing to enjoy the Liberties of the ſame, do contribute, <hi>(viz.)</hi> every one according to his abilities, to do Service to Us and Our Heirs with their Navy, whenſoever they ſhall be commanded by Us and Our Heirs. In witneſs whereof We have cauſed theſe Our Letters to be made Patents. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Our Self at St. <hi>Albans</hi> the Twenty eigth day of <hi>April,</hi> in the Twenty ſixth year of Our Reign.</p>
               <p>And we Ratifying the Grants and Confirmations aforeſaid, do grant and confirm them to be well pleaſing to Us and Our Heirs as much as in Us lyeth, for the Barons aforeſaid of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> their Heirs and Succeſſors, for
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:32072:9"/> their good and faithful Service which they have hitherto paid to Us, and ſhall pay for the future, as the Chatters and Letters aforeſaid do reaſonably teſtifie. And We further willing to do the ſaid Barons a greater kindneſs, have given and granted to them, for Us and Our Heirs, That although they have not hitherto enjoyed any one or more of their Liberties and Priviledges con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the ſaid Charters and Letters, yet the ſaid Barons, their Heirs and Succeſſors, may uſe and enjoy their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Priviledges aforeſaid, and every of them, without the let of Us or Our Heirs, or Our Officers whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. Witneſs hereunto, the Reverend Fathers, <hi>William</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter, J.</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Bath and Wells,</hi> and <hi>W.</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Exeter, Gilbert de Clare</hi> Earl of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> and <hi>Hereford, John de Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tann.</hi> Earl of <hi>Richmond, Adam de Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentia</hi> Earl of <hi>Pembroke, Hugh de le Spencer, Robert</hi> Son of <hi>Pagan, Edmund de malo Lacu,</hi> Steward of Our Houſhld, and others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Given under Our Hand at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> the Twenty ſixth day of <hi>July,</hi> in the Seventh year of Our Reign.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:32072:9"/>
               <p>We making Good the Grants and Confirmations aforeſaid, do Ratifie, and by the Tenour of the Preſents con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm them to be well pleaſing to Us and Our Heirs, as much as in Us lies, for the aforeſaid Barons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> their Heirs and Succeſſors, for the good and faithful Service hitherto paid to Us and Our Progenitors, and for the future to be paid to Us and Our Heirs, as the Charters and Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters aforeſaid do reaſonably teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie. And further willing to do to the aforeſaid Barons a greater kindneſs, We have granted for Us and Our Heirs to the ſame Barons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> That although they or their Predeceſſors hitherto have not fully en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed any one or more of their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Acquitances contained in the Charters and Letters aforeſaid, yet the ſaid Barons, their Heirs and Succeſſors, may fully enjoy, for ever make uſe of their Liberties and Acquitances afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, without any let or impediment of Us, Our Heirs, or any of Our Officers whatſoever. The Witneſſes hereunto are the Reverend Fathers, <hi>S.</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ely,</hi> Lord Chancellor, <hi>J.</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Bath and Wells,</hi> Our Treaſurer, <hi>Lionel</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:32072:10"/> Duke of <hi>Clarence, John</hi> Duke of <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſter, Edmund</hi> Earl of <hi>Kent,</hi> Our moſt dear Sons; <hi>Edward de le Spencer, Guydo, Brian, John Atley,</hi> Steward of Our Houſhold, and others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Given under Our Hand at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> the Firſt day of <hi>July</hi> in the Thirty eighth Year of Our Reign.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We have alſo look'd upon the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters-Patents of the ſame Our Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father after theſe words, <hi>Edward,</hi> by the Grace of God, King of <hi>England,</hi> Lord of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Duke of <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> To all thoſe to whom theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Letters ſhall come, Greeting. We have look'd upon Our Charter of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, which We lately made to the Barons of Our <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> under the Seal which We then uſed, after theſe words, <hi>Edward,</hi> by the Grace of God, King of <hi>England,</hi> Lord of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and Duke of <hi>Aquitain,</hi> To all thoſe to whom theſe preſent Letters ſhall come, Greeting. We have look'd upon Our Charter of Confirmation, which we lately made under the Seal which We then uſed, to the Barons of Our <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> after theſe words: <hi>Edward,</hi> by the Grace of God, King
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:32072:10"/> of <hi>England,</hi> Lord of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Duke of <hi>Aquitain,</hi> To all thoſe to whom theſe preſent Letters ſhall come Greet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. We have look'd upon the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters-Patents which the Lord <hi>Edward,</hi> of famous Memory, late King of <hi>England,</hi> Our Grandfather, made according to theſe words: <hi>Edward,</hi> by the Grace of God, King of <hi>England,</hi> Lord of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and Duke of <hi>Aquitain,</hi> To all thoſe to whom theſe preſent Letters ſhall come, Greeting. We conſidering that the Navy of the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſuſtained without great Coſts and Charges, left the Navy for the future ſhould fail or decay, We have grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Us and Our Heirs, That all the Members of the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> aforeſaid, and other Advocants and Reſiants what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever in the Liberties of the ſame, do contribute, <hi>(viz.)</hi> every of them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their abilities, for the doing the Service with their Ships to Us and Our Heirs, whenever by Us or Our Heirs they ſhall be commanded there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. In Witneſs whereof we have cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed theſe Our Letters to be made Patents.</p>
               <p>Witneſs Our Self at St. <hi>Albans</hi> the 28 day of <hi>April,</hi> in the 26 Year of Our Reign.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:32072:11"/>
               <p>And we Ratifying the Grant afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, do grant and confirm it to be well pleaſing to Us and Our Heirs, as the aforeſaid Letters do reaſonably teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie: And becauſe about thoſe general words contained in the Letters afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, <hi>viz.</hi> (that every one contribute according to his Abilities) there have riſen in former times divers diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; That the Barons of the Ports afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid may the more commodiouſly pay their aforeſaid Service to Us and Our Heirs at fit times, We have given and granted, by the Advice of Our Prelates, Earls, and Barons, and the Commons of Our Realm aſſembled together in Our preſent Parliament, to the ſaid Barons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> that all the Members of the ſaid Ports, and all Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocants and Reſiants whatſoever in the Liberties of the ſame, contribute to the Navy and Service aforeſaid, to be kept and maintained out of all their Goods and Chattels, as well thoſe that are without the Liberty of the aforeſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> as within, and may be compelled thereunto by the Mayors and Jurats of the Ports aforeſaid, and alſo, if need be, by the Conſtable of Our
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:32072:11"/> Caſtle of <hi>Dover:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Goods of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocants and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> not to be taxed with the Goods of Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners.</note> And that the Goods and Chattels of the ſaid Barons, and others, as well without the ſaid Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as within, which are taxed for the maintenance of the Navy, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming that Service, be by no means taxed for Tallage, and other Tributes, with the Goods and Chattels of Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners. In witneſs whereof We have cauſed theſe Our Letters to be made Patents.</p>
               <p>Witneſs Our Self at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the Twenty fifth day of <hi>February,</hi> in the Firſt year of Our Reign.</p>
               <p>And We thought fit to have a Copy of Our Charter aforeſaid under the Seal, which We now uſe to be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crib'd according to their requeſt. In Witneſs whereof We have cauſed theſe Our Letters to be made Patents.</p>
               <p>Witneſs Our Self at <hi>York</hi> the Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſixth day of <hi>February,</hi> in the Second year of Our Reign.</p>
               <p>And We Ratifying the Grants and Confirmations aforeſaid, as well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, for Us and Our Heirs, as much as in Us lyeth, do grant and confirm to the aforeſaid Barons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:32072:12"/> their Heirs and Succeſſors the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> aforeſaid, for their good and faithful Service to Us and Our Progenitors hitherto paid, and for the future to be paid to Us and Our Heirs, their Liberties, as the Charters and Letters aforeſaid do reaſonably teſtifie, and as the ſaid Barons, and their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors the Barons of the Ports afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid have hitherto lawfully uſed and enjoyed their Liberties and Acquitances aforeſaid. In Witneſs whereof We have cauſed theſe Our Letters to be made Patents.</p>
               <p>Witneſs Our Self at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the Twenty ſecond day of <hi>January,</hi> in the Firſt year of Our Reign.</p>
               <p>And We being certified by the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Petition of the ſaid Barons, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Men of the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> aforeſaid, and their Members, That notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, it is contained in the <hi>Magna Charta</hi> of the Liberties of <hi>England,</hi> (amonſt other things) that the Barons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> may have all their Liberties and Free-Cuſtoms, yet they, by reaſon of the ambiguity, obſcurity, and doubtful meaning of certain Words, and general Terms contained in the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:32072:12"/> Charters, Letters, and Confirmations aforeſaid, have been, and are at this time hindered from the enjoying of certain of their Liberties and Free-Cuſtoms, as alſo the Priviledges and Acquitances which they were wont freely, peaceably, and quietly to enjoy in the Ports aforeſaid, and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof, from the time of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Charters, Letters, and Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations aforeſaid, to the impoveriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and undoing of the ſaid Barons and Honeſt Men, as alſo to the damage of the Service of Our Navy, and the utter loſs thereof likely to enſue: We there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, greatly conſidering not only the premiſed, but alſo the good, volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and free Service which the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Barons and Honeſt Inhabitants of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> and Members afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, have paid to Our Progenitors, and eſpecially to Us in the reſtoring the Rights of Our Kingdom; And willing likewiſe to ſecure their Peace and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility, and the publick Good on this behalf, and making good to them, and well pleaſing to Us and Our Heirs, as much as in Us lies, all the Grants and Priviledges aforeſaid, as alſo all and every of them which are contained and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:32072:13"/> ſpecified in the Charters, Letters, and Confirmations aforeſaid, and all and every of their Liberties, Priviledges, Acquitances, and Free-Cuſtoms which they, their Anceſtors and Predeceſſors, had, and uſed in the time of Our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors, and which they were wont to enjoy, and poſſeſs, do accept, approve, and ratifie them; And to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Barons of the Ports and Members aforeſaid, and to their Heirs, and Succeſſors, by the tenour of theſe Preſents, do give, grant, and confirm as fully, plainly, and entirely, as if they had been word for word ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, declared, and manifeſted in theſe Preſents: We willing more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, and granting for Us and Our Heirs aforeſaid, that the aforeſaid Barons, and their Heirs and Succeſſors of the Ports and Members aforeſaid, ſhall have all their Liberties, Acquitances, Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and Free-Cuſtoms reſtor'd to them as fully and entirely as their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors and Predeceſſors had them in the times of St. <hi>Edmund the Confeſſor,</hi> and <hi>William the Conqueror,</hi> late Kings of <hi>England,</hi> or any other of Our Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, more freely, fully, and honorably. And although the ſaid Barons, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:32072:13"/> Honeſt Inbabitants, or their Anceſtors and Predeceſſors the Barons and Honeſt Inhabitants of the Ports and Members aforeſaid, or any of them, by ſome emergent chance have not yet fully en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed or perhaps miſuſed, any one or more of the Liberties, Acquitances, Priviledges, and Free-Cuſtoms contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſaid Charter and Letters; yet the Barons and Honeſt Inhabitants, their Heirs and Succeſſors, for the future ſhall fully uſe and enjoy the Liberties and Acquitances, Priviledges, and Free-Cuſtoms whatſoever, ſo not-uſed, or miſ-uſed,<note place="margin">Any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</note> or any of them, without any hindrance or let occaſioned by Us or Our Heirs, Juſtices, Sheriffs, Coroners, Eſcheators, or other Bailiffs or Officers to Us or Our Heirs whatſoever, any interruption had or made in time paſt to the contrary, in any wiſe notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. We have alſo granted for Us and Our Heirs, and by this Our Charter have confirmed to the Mayors, Bailiffs, and Jurats of every Port and Member of the Ports, and Members aforeſaid which were choſen in the Ports and Members aforeſaid by the Commons of the ſame, That if any Cuſtoms hitherto granted and uſed in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:32072:14"/> the Ports and Members of them, or any of them, be doubtful or defective in any part; or if any differences ariſing afreſh concerning them in the ſame Ports and Members, or in any of them, where there hath not been a Remedy former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made, ſhall want new ordering and reforming, that the ſaid Mayors, Bailiffs, and Jurats of every Port and Member of the Ports, and of the Members afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and their Heirs and Succeſſors, with the aſſent of the Commons of that Port or Member of the Ports, and of the Members aforeſaid, where this amendment, defect, or difficulty ſhall happen to be made or had, May ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point a Remedy agreeable to Honeſty and Reaſon,<note place="margin">A fit Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed.</note> for the common good of the Barons and Honeſt Men, and Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the ſame Port or Member of that Port, as alſo other of Our faithful Subjects reſorting thither, as often as they ſhall ſee it expedient; Provided that that Ordinance be profitable to Us and Our Subjects, and agreeable to Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as aforeſaid; And that they may Record their Liberties and Free-Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms before Us, Our Juſtices, or other Our Officers whatſoever. And further, that the ſame Barons may be encouraged
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:32072:14"/> for the future to pay as good Service, or to their utmoſt ability Better to Us and Our Heirs, then they paid Our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Progenitors and Us in times paſt, We have thought fit that other Liberties and Acquitances, plain and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, be granted anew to the ſame Barons and Honeſt Men. And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over of Our ſpecial Grace, meer Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and certain Knowledge, We have granted, and by theſe Preſents do grant for Us and Our Heirs, as much as in Us lies, to the ſame Barons and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Men of the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> aforeſaid, and to the Barons and Honeſt Men of all and ſingular the Ports, Towns, and Members adjoining, united, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to the ſame <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> or any of them, that they, their Heirs and Succeſſors, and other Reſiants whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever within the Ports and Members aforeſaid, or within any of the ſame, contributing to the Service and Navy aforeſaid, be for ever quit from Toll, Panage, Bridg-toll, Wharfage, Murage, Paſſage, Laſtage, Stallage, Tallage, Carriage, Weight-toll, Picage, Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tax, Scot, and Gild, Hidage, Eſcuage, and alſo from the Suits of County and Hundred (and Tributes of Hundreds)
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:32072:15"/> from the View of Free-Pledges, and the Pence belonging to the View of Free-Pledges; as alſo from whatſoever Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, Returns, or Payments to be paid to Us, Our Heirs, or Our Succeſſors, for any of the Premiſes aforeſaid; And from Fines for Murder, and common Amercement whenſoever it happen that a County or Town before Us or Our Heirs, or before Us, or whatſoever Our Juſtices, Officers or Miniſters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, fall into the hands of Us or Our Heirs; and from all ſuch like Cuſtom, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Our whole Realm and Dominions. And We have alſo granted to the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Barons and Honeſt Men, their Heirs and Succeſſors, That for ever they may have all Goods and Chattels Waviated, or which are ſeized by Waife, and alſo all Goods and Chattels which are count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Stray; as alſo any Treaſure which is or ſhall be found within the Ports aforeſaid, or any Member of the ſame; And the Goods and Chattels which are ſaid to be made by the hand that are taken, or ſhall be took with any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereſoever within the Ports and Members aforeſaid, being before any Judge whatſoever diſavowed by the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:32072:15"/> ſame perſon. And that the ſaid Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons and Honeſt Men, their Heirs and Succeſſors the Barons and Honeſt Men of the Ports and Members afor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſaid, ſhall have the Chattels of whatſoever Felons condemned or convicted, or here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to be condemned or convicted; And the Goods forfeited for the eſcape of Felons, and Fines whatſoever for the ſame Eſcapes in whatſoever Courts belonging to Us or Our Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, they be Aſſeſſed or hereafter ſhall be Aſſeſſed before Us or Our Heirs, or or the Juſtices and Judges belonging to Us or Our Heirs whatſoever; And alſo the Chattels of all other Perſons which are or ſhall be demanded in a Writ <hi>Exigent</hi> for Appearance, or for Felony; And alſo the Chattels of thoſe which are Outlawed and Waviated, or ſhall be Outlawed or Waviated; And the Chattels by what means ſoever confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, and of all and ſingular the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons and other Reſiants whatſoever within the Ports and Members afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, whereſoever theſe Goods and Chattels ſhall happen to be found with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Ports and Members aforeſaid, or without them, in the Counties of <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Suſſex,</hi> or either of them, although
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:32072:16"/> the Officers and Servants of Us or Our Heirs, or any one of them be there preſent. And that the ſaid Barons and Honeſt Men, and their Succeſſors, ſhall for ever have the Wreck of the Sea at whatſoever Coaſts and Arms of the Sea in the Ports and Members aforeſaid adjacent it ſhall happen to be caſt, and all and ſingular the things which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long and appertain to ever ſuch Wreck: And that they, their Heirs and Succeſſors, ſhall either in their own Perſons, or by their Servants, take and ſeize upon, for their own uſe, ſuch Chattels which are counted Waif or Strey, any Treaſure found, Chattels which are ſaid to be made by the hand, Chattels of Felons by whatſoever means condemned or to be condemned, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed or to be convicted, the Chattels of all perſons whatſoever which are or ſhall be demanded in a Writ <hi>Exigent</hi> for Appearance, or for Felony; the Chattels of thoſe which are or ſhall be Outlawed, and which are or ſhall be Waifed; and Chattels by what means ſoever confiſcated, and the Wreck, with all things belonging to ſuch Wreck; without the trouble, moleſtation, or impediment of Us or Our Heirs, the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:32072:16"/> Juſtices, Eſcheators, Sheriffs, Coroners, or other Bailiffs belonging to Us or Our Heirs, or any others whatſoever, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they were ſeized heretofore by Us or Our Heirs, or ſome of the Bailiffs, Officers, and Servants to Us and Our Heirs. We have alſo granted for Us and Our Heirs, to the aforeſaid Barons and Honeſt Men, their Heirs and Succeſſors, for the better maintaining of the Navy, and Service aforeſaid, That every Mayor and Jurat in every Port and Member of the Ports and Members aforeſaid, where there is a Mayor and Jurats; and every Bailiff and Jurat in every Port and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the ſame Ports and Members where ſuch Bailiff is choſen by he Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the Inhabitants of that Port or Member of the Ports or of the Members aforeſaid; And alſo the Jurats in every Port and Member of the aforeſaid Ports and Members, where neither the Mayor nor Bailiff is choſen by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the Inhabitants of that Port or Member and their Succeſſors, ſhall for ever receive all and all manner of Fines for Treſpaſſes, Offences, Miſpriſions, Wrongs, Negligences, Ignorances, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies, Concealments, Regraters, Foreſtallers, Maintenances, Bribes,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:32072:17"/> Champarties, Counterfeitings, Cheats, Contempts, and all other defaults what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever: As alſo the Fines for a Licence of Agreements, and all Amercements, Redemptions, Exits, and Penalties which are or ſhall be forfeited; a year and a day, Waſte and Strip, and all that which ſhould belong to Us and Our Heirs from ſuch a year, and a day, Waſt, and Strip of all and ſingular the Barons and other Reſiants aforeſaid, their Heirs and Succeſſors, as well with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Ports and Members aforeſaid, as without; And the ſaid Barons, and other ſuch like Reſiants in all the Courts whatſoever belonging to Us and Our Heirs, ſhall Impoſe Fines, Aſſeſs <hi>Exits,</hi> and make Forfeiture for Penalties, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judge a year and a day, Waſt and Strip, and ſuch like Forfeitures; Which Fines and Amercements, Redemptions, Exits, Penalties, a year and a day, Waſt and Strip, Forfeitures, ſhall belong to Us and Our Heirs, unleſs they have been granted to the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Barons and Honeſt Men, and their Succeſſors: So that the ſaid May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors and Jurats, and alſo the Jurats in every Port and Member of the Ports and Members before-nam'd, elected as
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:32072:17"/> it is aforeſaid, ſhall in their own Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or by their Servants, levy, take, and receive ſuch Fines, Amercements, Redemptions, Exits, Penalties, and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures, and all other things which ſhould belong to Us, Our Heirs, and Succeſſors for a year and a day, waſte, ſtrip, and the Forfeitures aforſaid, for the common profit and uſe of the ſaid Barons, their Heirs and Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, without the impediment of Us or Our Heirs, Juſtices, Bailiffs, or other Our Officers whatſoever: And that the ſaid Barons and Honeſt Men, their Heirs and Succeſſors, may have as it ſhall ſeem good to them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in every Port and Member of the Ports and Members aforeſaid, a Pillory for Thieves, and a Cucking-ſtooll for the puniſhment of Offenders there; And alſo that they and their Succeſſors may for ever have Leets, and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days, with all the Profits which way ſoever belonging or appertaining there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto from any Reſiants whoſoever with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Liberty aforeſaid: And that the aforeſaid Barons and Honeſt Men, and their Heirs and Succeſſors from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward, and every of them may have whatever they find upon Land and Sea
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:32072:18"/> freely, peaceably, and quietly, without any impediment or diſturbance by Us or Our Heirs, or by the Conſtables to Us or Our Heirs of Our Caſtle of <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> or by the Admiral of the Cinque-Ports, or Admiral within the Ports and Members aforeſaid, without any diviſion of it to be made, or any part of it to be rendred to Us or Our Heirs, or any other: And we have further granted for Us and Our Heirs, as much as in Us lieth, to the aforeſaid Barons and Honeſt Men, and to their Heirs and Succeſſors Liberty to Erect Gallowes within every Port and Member of the Ports and Members aforeſaid; And to give Judgment upon all Offenders who ſhall happen to be taken and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended there according to the above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Priviledge of Infangtheff and Utfangtheff, and according to the cuſtom antiently uſed in the Ports and Members aforeſaid, without the lett, queſtioning, or impediment of Us or Our Heirs, Juſtices, Coroners, Eſchea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, Sheriffs, or other Our Bayliffs, and Officers whoſoever: And that the ſaid Mayor and Jurats, Bayliffs and Jurats, and alſo the Jurats in every Port and Member of the Ports and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:32072:18"/> Members aforeſaid as they are before limited, may and ſhall from henceforth have and hold before the fame Mayor and Jurats, Bailiff and Jurats, and alſo Jurats, by a Complaint before them to be relieved in the Court of any Port or Member of the Ports and Members aforeſaid, in any place, days or times moſt conveniently to be held according to cuſtom within any ſuch Port or Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, all and all ſorts of Pleas of and concerning all ſorts of Actions, real, perſonal, and mixt, happening by Sea or Land within any ſuch Port or Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; And that they may attach thoſe Perſons, and commit their Bodies to Priſon, againſt whom ſuch Perſonal Actions ſhall happen to be ſued or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, and be Oyers and Terminers of all and every the aforeſaid Pleas, and give Judgment upon Proceſs and Executions to be done according to the cuſtom of the Ports aforeſaid; ſo that neither the Conſtable to Us or Our Heirs of the Caſtle of <hi>Dover</hi> aforeſaid, nor the Warden of the Cinque-Ports aforeſaid, nor the Admiral of the fame, nor any Vice-gerent, nor Deputy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by him, ſhall about or concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any ſuch Plea within the Ports and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:32072:19"/> Members aforeſaid, or about any other Buſineſs or Matter that is or happens, or ſhall be or happen by Land, or Sea, by Freſh Water, or bounds and banks of the deep Sea, in any wiſe come within the limits and liberties of the ſame Ports and Members, or enter into ſuch Port or Member upon ſuch an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count in any wiſe whatſoever, unleſs in default of the Mayor, Bailiff, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats not adminiſtring Juſtice; And if ſuch default ſhall chance to be, then We Will that only the aforeſaid Warden of the Cinque-Ports aforeſaid for the time being, either by Word of Mouth or Petition to be made by the party which ſhall perceive himſelf to be wronged, enter into the ſaid Port or Member from time to time, and cauſe the Plea touching this defect to come before him within the ſame Port and Member in the preſence of ſuch Mayor, Bailiff, and Jurats, and there examine the Plea aforeſaid, and correct and amend ſuch default, if there be any, and there adminiſter with ſpeed full and compleat Juſtice to all and every of them who have any occaſion to be there preſent; according to law and cuſtom: And that the Mayor and Jurats, Bailiff
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:32072:19"/> and Jurats, and the Jurats aforeſaid o every Port and Member of the Ports and Members aforeſaid, elected in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and form aforeſaid, ſhall for ever have the Cognizance, as well of all ſorts of Pleas in the actions above-named, as of all ſorts of Pleas belonging to the Crown, any way happening within every ſuch Ports or Members; And the Power of hearing and determining all pleas belonging to the Crown of Us or Our Heirs, as well at the Suit of Us and Our Heirs, as at the Suit of other Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffs (the Pleas of all ſorts of Treaſons only excepted) which We Will for Us and Our Heirs, as much as in Us lieth, to be heard and determined before the Warden for the time being of the Cinque-Ports aforeſaid, the Mayors, Bailiffs, and Jurats of the ſame Ports being ſummoned according to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom uſed in the ſame Ports, at <hi>Shepey,</hi> according to the Law and Cuſtom of the Court aforeſaid: And that every ſuch Mayor and Jurats, Bailiff and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats, as alſo the Jurats as above limited, may at their Election have and hold all and ſingular the Pleas abovenamed (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting thoſe which are afore excepted) before them within every ſuch Port and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:32072:20"/> Member, in the Court of the ſame Port or Member; and may hear and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine all ſuch Pleas, and execute Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments given upon them according to the Law and Cuſtom of Our Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> or Cuſtom of the Cinque-Ports aforeſaid: And further, that none of the aforeſaid Barons, Honeſt Men, or their Heirs and Succeſſors, or Reſiants aforeſaid, for the future ſhall be taken, Arreſted, or Attach'd by any Warrants, Precepts, or Commandment of the Conſtable of the Caſtle aforeſaid, or of the Warden of the Cinque-Ports aforeſaid, or Admiral within the Ports and Members aforeſaid, to anſwer upon any ſuch Plea; or be bound in any wiſe to appear upon the ſame Cauſe before the ſame Conſtable, Warden, or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral, or his Vice-gerent, or Deputy, unleſs upon default of not adminiſtring Juſtice as aforeſaid: And that none of the Barons, Honeſt Men, or their Heirs, or ſuch like Reſiants, ſhall for the future be in any wiſe Preſſed, Attach't, or Arreſted by any of the Officers and Miniſters of Us or Our Heirs, to or for the Service of Us or Our Heirs to be performed upon the Sea, except for the Service of the ſaid Barons to be
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:32072:20"/> paid to Us and Our Heirs with their Navy, as aforeſaid: We have further granted to the above-named Barons and Honeſt Men, that they, their Heirs and Succeſſors and other Reſiants whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever of their Heirs and Succeſſors, within the Ports and Members afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, who do now or ſhall hereafter contribute to the Service and Navy aforeſaid, be for ever free from all Aids, Subſidies,<note place="margin">They ſhall be free from all Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> Contributions, Tallage, and all other how many ſoever, which, if the grant aforeſaid made to them had not been, ſhould or might have been exacted of them, or of any of them, by Us or Our Heirs, by the Bailiffs or Officers of Us or Our Heirs, upon the account of their Lands, Tenements, and Incomes, or their Goods and Chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels, or any thing belonging to them which they now have, and from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth are to poſſeſs: And that whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Commons of the Counties of Our Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> or the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens and Burgeſſes of the Cities and Burroughs of the ſaid Counties have any way granted to Us, Our Heirs, or Succeſſors, the Tenth, Fifteenth, or any other Sum or Tax whatſoever, of their Goods moveable, or Lands, Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:32072:21"/> or other of their Incoms; Or that We or Our Heirs have cauſed Our Tenths to be be levied throughout <hi>England,</hi> the ſaid Barons, their Heirs and Succeſſors, and the Ports and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers aforeſaid, the Lands, Tenements, and Goods and Chattels of the Barons, their Heirs and Succeſſors, and of other Reſiants aforeſaid, or of any of them, whether they be within the Liberties of the ſaid Ports and Members, or without in the Counties of <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Suſſex,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Within or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex,</hi> they ſhall not be Tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> ſhall not be Taxed for the Uſe of Us or Our Heirs; Nor ſhall any thing in any wiſe be levied upon them ſor Tenths, Fifteenths, and other Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes or Tallages aforeſaid for the Uſe of Us or Our Heirs; Nor ſhall the ſaid Barons, their Heirs or Succeſſors, or other Reſiants aforeſaid, be diſtreined, moleſted, or diſturbed upon theſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts in any thing concerning their Lands, Tenements, or their Goods aforeſaid; but that they, their Heirs and Succeſſors, be for ever free from all manner of Tenths, Fifteenths, and other ſuch like Tributes and Tallages, although they themſelves or any of them be Agents in ſuch Grants: And We have further granted for Us and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:32072:21"/> Our Heirs to the aforeſaid Barons and Honeſt Men, that none of them, their Heirs and Succeſſors ſhall for the future be put in any Aſſizes, Juries, Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zances, Attaints, or other Inquiſitions whatſoever without the Ports and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers aforeſaid, although they concern Us or Our Heirs; And that none of them be made an Aſſeſſor, Taxer, or Collector of Tenths, Fifteenths, or any parcel of them, or other Subſidies, Tallages, Taxes, or ſmall Summs what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever which are or ſhall be granted to Us or Our Heirs; Nor be Collector of the reaſonable Aid for the creating the Eldeſt Son of Us or Our Heirs a Knight, or for the Marrying the Eldeſt Son of Us or Our Heirs; Nor ſhall any of them be choſen or appointed Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, Bailiff, or other Officer and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to Us or Our Heirs, without the Ports and Members aforeſaid, againſt his Will; And in caſe that any of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Barons, Honeſt Men, or their Heirs and Succeſſors, be for the future choſen, ordained, or appointed to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo and perform the trouble of any of the Offices or Employments aforeſaid; or to undergo, perform, or take any other Office againſt the force, tenour,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:32072:22"/> and efficacy of this our preſent Grant, although he ſhall refuſe to undergo, perform, or take upon him thoſe Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices or Troubles, yet he ſhall in no wiſe upon that account incur any Fine, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, Forfeit, loſs or damage upon his Body or Goods; but that Our preſent Letters ſhewed upon Record by him before any Juſtices and Officers whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever to Us and Our Heirs, in whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever place through Our whole Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> ſhall upon that declaration remain in their force and virtue, and by that ſhall be allowed to do the ſame without any Writ or Proceſs to be thence further proſecuted: And that whenſoever there ſhall happen any Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations to be made before Our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable of Our Caſtle of <hi>Dover,</hi> or before the Warden of the Cinque-Ports afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, or Admiral of the fame, ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitions ſhall be had, taken and done within that Port or Member of the Ports and Members aforeſaid, where they of the reſpective Ports and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, by whom theſe Inquiſitions ſhall be taken, do live and dwell, and no where elſe; And that they who are mentioned and Empannelled in the Inquiries afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid ſhall no way be bound, compelled,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:32072:22"/> or forced to go out of their reſpective Port or Member to any other place, to take their Charge or deliver their Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict; Nor ſhall they nor any of them any way upon that account incur any contempt, amerciament, penalty, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture, or any loſs, to Us or Our Heirs. Wherefore We Will and ſtrictly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for Us and Our Heirs,<note place="margin">Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore We Will.</note> that the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Barons and Honeſt Men of the Ports aforeſaid, their Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, have all and ſingular the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Acquitances aforeſaid, and all the Premiſes by Us renewed to them and every of them; and that for the future without any impediment of Us or Our Heirs,<note place="margin">Without impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> or Our Officers whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, they for ever uſe and enjoy them; Witneſs hereunto the Reverend Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late <hi>Thomas</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> and Primate of all <hi>England,</hi> Our moſt Dear Brothers <hi>George</hi> Duke of <hi>Clare,</hi> and <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Priors <hi>George</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Exon</hi> Our Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London, Richard</hi> Earl of <hi>Warwick,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> Earl of <hi>Northumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> Our moſt dear Coſins, as alſo Our Truſty and Well-beloved Mr. <hi>Robert Stillington</hi> Keeper of Our Privy-Seal,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:32072:23"/> and <hi>Walter Blunt</hi> Knt. Our Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> and others; Given under Our Hand at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the Twenty third day of <hi>March</hi> in the Fifth year of Our Reign: But We Ratifying and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Charters and Letters aforeſaid, and all and ſingular the things contained in them, do accept and approve of them for Us and Our Heirs, as much as in Us lieth, and by the Tenor of theſe Preſents do Ratifie and Confirm them to Our Well-beloved Barons and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Men of the ſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> and Members of the ſame, and to their Heirs and Succeſſors, as the Charters and Letters aforeſaid do reaſonably Teſtifie: In Witneſs whereof We have cauſed theſe Our Letters to be made Patents, Witneſs Our Self at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> the Thirteenth day of <hi>December,</hi> in the Third year of Our Reign. But We Ratifying and likeing well the Charters and Letters aforeſaid, and all and ſingular the things contained in them, do accept and approve of them for Us and Our Heirs, as much as in Us lieth, and by the Tenor of theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents do Ratifie and Confirm them to Our Well-beloved Barons and Honeſt Men of the ſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> and their
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:32072:23"/> Members, and to their Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, as the Charters and Letters aforeſaid do reaſonably Teſtifie: In Witneſs whereof We have cauſed theſe Our Letters to be made Patents, Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Our Self at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the Fifth day of <hi>March,</hi> in the firſt year of Our Reign. But We Ratifying and likeing well the Charters and Letters afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and all and ſingular the things contained in them, do accept and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of them for Us and Our Heirs, as much as in Us lieth, and by the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of theſe Preſents do Ratifie and Confirm them to Our Well-beloved Barons and Honeſt Men of the ſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> and their Members and to their Heirs and Succeſſors, as the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Letters aforeſaid do reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably Teſtifie: In Witneſs whereof We have cauſed theſe Our Letters to be made Patents, Witneſs Our Self at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the Twentieth day of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> in the Second year of Our Reign. But We Ratifying and likeing well the Charters and Letters aforeſaid, and all and ſingular the things contained in them, do accept and approve of them for Us and Our Heirs, as much as in Us lieth, and by the Tenor of theſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:32072:24"/> Preſents do Ratifie and Confirm them to Our Well-beloved Barons and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Men of the ſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> and their Members, and to their Heirs and Succeſſors, as the Charters and Letters aforeſaid do reaſonably Teſtifie: In Witneſs whereof we have cauſed theſe Our Letters to be made Patents, Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Our Self at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the Twenty ſeventh day of <hi>October,</hi> in the Firſt year of Our Reign. But We Ratifying and likeing well the Charters and Letters aforeſaid, and all and ſingular the things contained in them, do accept and approve of them for Us and Our Heirs, as much as in Us lieth, and by the Tenor of theſe Preſents do Ratifie and Confirm them to Our Well-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Barons and Honeſt Men of the ſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> and their Members, and to their Heirs and Succeſſors, as the Charters and Letters aforeſaid do reaſonably Teſtifie: In Witneſs where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of We have cauſed theſe Our Letters to be made Patents, Witneſs Our Self at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the Eigth day of <hi>March,</hi> in the Firſt year of Our Reign. We have alſo looked upon the Letters Patents of the ſaid Lady <hi>Elizabeth</hi> late Queen, about the Grants to the Barons
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:32072:24"/> of the ſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> and Towns of <hi>Rye</hi> and <hi>Winchelſea,</hi> and Members of the ſame Ports and Towns, and every of them, and to their Succeſſors the Barons of the ſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Towns, and Members, made after theſe words:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Elizabeth</hi> by the Grace of God,<note place="margin">We have look'd upon the Charters of <hi>Eliz.</hi> about Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenths.</note> Queen of <hi>England, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To the Treaſurer, Chancellor, and Barons of Our Exchequer for the time being, and to all other the Officers, Miniſters, and Subjects of Us, Our Heirs and Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors for the time being, or which here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſhall be, to whom it ſhall or may appertain, and to every of them Greet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Whereas it appeareth unto Us by one Record remaining in Our Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, amongſt the Records of the Term of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> in the Sixth year of the Reign of Our moſt Dear Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father King <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, That <hi>John Convers</hi> of <hi>Winchelſea,</hi> and <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Warwyn</hi> of <hi>Dover</hi> Combons of the five Ports, did come before the Barons of the ſame Exchequer the Seventh day of <hi>May,</hi> in that ſame Term of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> in their proper Perſons, and did exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite to the ſaid Court there, a certain
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:32072:25"/> Letter of Attorney, Sealed with the Common Seal of the Mayors, Bayliffs, Jurats, and Barons of the five Ports, and directed to the Treaſurer and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons of the ſame Exchequer, the Tenor whereof followeth in theſe words; To the Right, Mighty, and Noble Lord, <hi>John Dynham</hi> Knt. Lord <hi>Dynham,</hi> High Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> and to the full Honourable the Barons of our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Lord the Kings Exchequer at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> that now be, We the Mayors, Bayliffs, Jurats, and Barons of the Towns and Ports of <hi>Haſting, Winchelſea, Rye, Romney, Heth, Dover,</hi> and <hi>Sandwich,</hi> at our Brotheryield-General at the ſaid Town and Port of <hi>Romney,</hi> the day of the Date hereof, Holden, Aſſembled, that is to ſay, <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Nepſham</hi> Bayliff of <hi>Haſting, Richard Martham</hi> Mayor of <hi>Winchelſea, John Cheeſeman</hi> Mayor of <hi>Rye, John Cheynew</hi> Jurate of <hi>Romney, Thomas Walton</hi> Jurate of <hi>Heth, Edward Hextal</hi> Mayor of <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Aldy</hi> Mayor of <hi>Sand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich,</hi> which ſend due Recommendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in all humblewiſe as appertaineth: And whereas it hath pleaſed our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Lord, by the Advice of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, is Agreed that the Suſtentation-Subſidy
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:32072:25"/> and maintenance of our Navy, to do our old Service to our Sovereign Lord the King, and to his Heirs Kings of <hi>England,</hi> That at every whole Fifteenth and Tenth hereafter by the Commons of this His Realm, to Him and to His Heirs to be granted, the Collectors of the ſame and every of them, within the Counties of <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Suſſex,</hi> from thenceforth ſhall have deduction in their Accompts betwixt them, by the Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificate of the ſaid Barons, ſo that they exceed not the Sum of Five hundred Pounds Sterling, for the Allowance of all Reſiants and Advocants of their Allowance of all ſuch Fifteens as from thenceforth ſhall be granted to our ſaid Sovereign Lord the King, and to His Heirs Kings of <hi>England,</hi> and from thenceforth to be gathered, and that his Highneſs willeth in that behalf, that we nor our Heirs ſhall not in any wiſe exceed the Sum of Five hundred Pounds, and that we ſhould thereupon be bound by Recognizance before His ſaid Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons in His ſaid Exchequer at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> to the accompliſhment of the ſame, We the ſaid Mayors, Bayliffs, Jurats, and Barons, certifie by theſe Preſents, that we, the day of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:32072:26"/> hereof, have given full Power and Authority to our Right Truſty, and Right Well-beloved Brethren and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bons, Mr. <hi>John Convers</hi> of the ſaid Town of <hi>Winchelſea,</hi> and <hi>William War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyn</hi> of the ſaid Town of <hi>Dover,</hi> our true and lawful Attorneys, joyntly and ſeverally in that behalf, by the Advice of Learned Councel, to bind us to our ſaid Sovereign Lord the King, and to His Heirs Kings of <hi>England,</hi> by Recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance in the ſaid Kings Exchequer, before the ſaid Barons in all due and convenient Form, and Sum reaſonable, after the ſaid Wiſdoms and Diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ſaid High-Treaſurer, and the ſaid Barons for the accompliſhment of the Premiſes, that is to ſay, That we nor our Heirs ſhall not from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth exceed the ſaid Sum of Five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Pound.</p>
               <p>In Witneſs whereof, we the ſaid Mayors, Bayliffs, Jurats, and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, the Seal of our ſaid Brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yield uſed and accuſtomed to theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Preſents, have put at the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Town and Port of <hi>Romney,</hi> th 12th day of <hi>April,</hi> in the Sixth yea of the Reign of our ſaid Sovereign Lord King <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50-100" type="part">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:32072:26"/>
               <p>Whereupon the ſaid <hi>John Convers</hi> and <hi>William Warwyn</hi> being then preſent in the ſaid Court in their proper Perſons, and admitted there by the Barons to be the Attorneys of the ſaid Mayors, Bayliffs, Jurats, and Barons of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Ports, to execute and do in all things according to the Tenor of the ſaid Letter; And the ſaid <hi>John</hi> and <hi>William</hi> taking upon them the ſame, did acknowledge the ſame Mayors, Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffs, Jurats, and Barons, to owe to Our ſaid Grandfather One thouſand Pound Sterling, to be paid to Our ſaid Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father in the Feaſt of the Nativity of St. <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt then next coming. And except they did perform it, the ſaid <hi>John</hi> and <hi>William</hi> in the ſtead and Name of the ſame Mayors, Bayliffs, Jurats, and Barons, did grant that Our Grandfather ſhould cauſe to be levied the ſaid Money, of the Lands and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements of the ſaid Mayors, Bayliffs, Jurats, and Barons, whereof they, or any others, or any other that were ſeized, and of their Goods and Chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels to whoſe hand ſoever they ſhould come, and made that this Recognizance was under ſuch Condition, That if the Collectors of the Fifteenths and Tenths
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:32072:27"/> to Our ſaid Grandfather, then, or to His Heirs Kings of <hi>England</hi> in the Counties of <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Suſſex,</hi> and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where within this Realm of <hi>England</hi> from henceforth to be granted, ſhould not have Deductions in their Accompts to Our ſaid Grandfather of ſuch whole Fifteenth and Tenth to be yielded by the Certificates of the Mayors, Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffs, Jurats, and Barons, or their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors from thenceforth to be above the Sum of 500 <hi>l.</hi>And if the ſaid Mayors, Bayliffs, Jurats, and Barons, their Heirs and Succeſſors, by their Certificates to ſuch Collectors in the ſaid Counties of <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Suſſex,</hi> and elſewhere within this Realm of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> of, and for ſuch whole Fifteenth and Tenth for the ſame Mayors, Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffs, Jurats, and Barons, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiants and Advocants of the ſaid Ports, to be made and directed, ſhould not exceed the Sum of 500 <hi>l.</hi> at every ſuch Fifteenth and Tenth thenceforth to be granted, that then the ſaid Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance ſhould be void, otherwiſe it ſhould remain in his ſtrength and effect as by the ſaid Record remaining in the Cuſtody of Our Remembrancer in Our Exchequer more at large appeareth.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:32072:27"/> And whereas further it appeareth unto Us by Letters under the Privy Seal of Our ſaid moſt dear Grandfather King <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, directed to Mr. Treaſurer and the Barons of his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, bearing Date at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the Three and Twentieth day of <hi>June</hi> in the Ninth year of His Reign, That whereas Our ſaid Grandfather was then informed, that of old time accuſtomed at every Fifteenth granted to the Barons of the five Ports, and their Advocants and Members of them, and every of them, were wont to be allowed in the Exchequer of Our ſaid Grandfather, of as much and as large Sums of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney as they would ask by ſufficient Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let thereof, at every Fifteenth granted till then of late by agreement thereof taken, and as between Our ſaid Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father and them, they were Ceſſed at a certain Sum of 500 <hi>l.</hi> and thereupon they were bound in a Recognizance before the Treaſurer and Barons of Our ſaid Grandfather in his Exchequer unto Our ſaid Grandfather, in One thouſand Marks, that they ſhould not exceed the ſaid Sum of 500 <hi>l.</hi> in asking Allowance by Billet, upon forfeiture to Our ſaid Grandfather of the ſaid Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:32072:28"/> Marks, And whereas Our ſaid Grandfather being informed, That the Treaſurer and Barons of His Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer did then deny to receive and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Bills and Billets under the Seals either of the Towns of <hi>Winchelſea</hi> and <hi>Rye,</hi> and of the Members of the ſaid five Ports, of every of them for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging of divers of the Collectors of Our ſaid Grandfather, for divers Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenths that then were paſt; Our ſaid Grandfather willing the ſaid five Ports, the ſaid Towns of <hi>Winchelſea</hi> and <hi>Rye,</hi> and the Members of them, and every of them to be Partners of the ſaid Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of 500 <hi>l.</hi> as they be Charged to Our ſaid Grandfather in Service, and for divers and many other great Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations Our ſaid Grandfather ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally moving, did by the ſaid Letters under the ſaid Privy Seal, Will and Charge the ſaid Treaſurer and Barons of his Exchequer and every of them, that they immediately after the ſight of the ſame Letters, ſhould receive and take of the Collector and Collectors of Our ſaid Grandfather of any ſuch Fifteenth, all ſuch Bills and Billets for diſcharging of the ſaid Fifteenths be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that time granted, and thereafter
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:32072:28"/> to be granted, as well them that were under the Seals of the ſaid Towns of <hi>Winchelſea</hi> and <hi>Rye</hi> parcel of the Head Ports, or any of them, as them that were under the Seals of any of the Members, to what manner of Sum that the ſaid Bills or Billets ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount unto. And if the ſaid Bills or Billets ſhould amount to the Sum of 500 <hi>l.</hi> or beneath at a Fifteen, then Our ſaid Grandfather Willed and Charged them and every of them to allow all the Sum of 500 <hi>l.</hi> or any Sum beneath that Sum; And if the ſaid Bills or Billets ſhould amount above the Sum of the ſaid 500 <hi>l.</hi> Then Our ſaid Granfather willed the ſaid Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer and Barons, that they allow to the ſaid Collectors the ſaid Sum of 500 <hi>l.</hi> and no more. And then Our ſaid Grandfather willed, that the ſaid Treaſurer and Barons ſhould make as haſty Proceſs as they lawfully might againſt the ſaid five Ports, for the ſaid Thouſand Marks by them unto Our ſaid Grandfather to be forfeited, for their exceeding the ſaid Sum contrary to their ſaid Recognizance, as by the ſaid Letters under the Privy Seal of Our ſaid Grandfather more at large appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:32072:29"/> And whereas divers of the moſt antient Charters, and Letters Patents, made to the Barons of the ſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> in that behalf, as alſo the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rollment of the ſame by length and tract of long time and many Ages, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe are periſhed, and utterly worn out, loſt, or decayed, We conſidering the good Services which the ſaid Barons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> and of the ſaid Towns of <hi>Rye</hi> and <hi>Winchelſea,</hi> and their Members have done unto Us, and the great Charges which they have been at in Our late Services upon the Seas, and elſewhere againſt the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> in the year of Our Lord God 1588. and 1596. and willing that the ſaid Barons of the ſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> and of the ſaid Towns of <hi>Rye</hi> and <hi>Winchelſea,</hi> and the Members of them, and every of them, and the Reſiants of the ſaid Ports, Towns, and Members, and the Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants of the ſaid Ports, and Towns, and every of them, ſhould be diſcharged of the Sum of 500 <hi>l.</hi> at every Fifteen, and be Partners of the ſaid Diſcharge of 500 <hi>l.</hi> according to ſuch rate and proportion as the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Towns, and Members be charged to Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors in Service and in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:32072:29"/> finding and maintaining of the Navy of the ſaid Port, Towns, and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers: In conſideration of the ſaid Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, and for the better maintenance and ſuſtentation of the Navy of the ſaid Ports, and for divers other good conſiderations, Us ſpecially moving of Our ſpecial Grace, meer motion, and certain knowledge do for Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors grant unto the ſaid Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons of the ſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> and of the ſaid Towns of <hi>Rye</hi> and <hi>Winchelſea,</hi> and of the Members of the ſame Ports, and Towns, and every of them and their Succeſſors; Barons of the ſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Towns, and Members, That at every Fifteenth heretofore to Us grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and yet payable, and heretofore to Us granted, and hereafter to be paid; And alſo at every Fifteenth hereafter to Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors to be granted, they the ſaid Barons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> and of the ſaid Towns of <hi>Rye</hi> and <hi>Winchelſea,</hi> and of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the ſaid Ports and Towns, and of every of them, and their Succeſſors Barons of the ſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Towns and Members for themſelves, and the Reſiants of the ſaid Ports, Towns, and Members, and the Advocants of the ſaid
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:32072:30"/> Ports, and Towns, ſhall have thereof, and be allowed in the Exchequer of Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors at, and of every ſuch Fifteenth ſo granted, or to be granted as is aforeſaid, the ſaid Sum of 500 <hi>l.</hi> and no more: And therefore for Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, We do Will and Charge the Treaſurer, Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, and Barons of the Exchequer of Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, and of every of them for the time being, for ever hereafter that they do from time to time, receive and take of the Collector and Collectors of any Fifteenth at any time heretofore to Us granted and yet paiable, and heretofore granted to Us, and hereafter to be paid, and hereafter to Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors to be granted, all ſuch Bills and Billets for the diſcarge of the ſaid Barons of Our ſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> and of the ſaid Towns of <hi>Rye</hi> and <hi>Winchelſea,</hi> and of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of them and every of them, and of the Reſiants of the ſaid Ports, Towns and Members, and the Advocants of the ſame Ports and Towns, and of every of them for the time being, of the Sum of 500 <hi>l.</hi> part or parcel of every ſuch Fifteenth before this time granted and yet payable, and heretofore granted
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:32072:30"/> unto Us, and hereafter to be paid, and hereafter to Us, Our Heirs or Succeſſors to be granted as well all thoſe Bills and Billets that be or hereafter ſhall be under the Seals of any of the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> and Towns of <hi>Rye</hi> and <hi>Winchelſea</hi> or any of them, as all thoſe which be or hereafter ſhall be, under the Seals of any of the Members of the ſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> and Towns, or any of them; And if the ſaid Bills or Billets, do or ſhall at any time hereafter of, or for any Fifteenth amount above the ſaid Sum of 500 <hi>l.</hi> then for Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, We Will and Charge the ſaid Treaſurer, Chancellor, and Barons of the ſame Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, and every of them from time to time, to allow to the ſaid Collector and Collectors of Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors for the time being, for the ſaid Barons of the ſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> and Towns of <hi>Rye</hi> and <hi>Winchelſea,</hi> and their Succeſſors, and for them and every of their Members, and the Reſiants of the ſaid Ports, Towns, and Members, and the Advocants of the ſaid Ports and Towns the ſaid Sum of 500 <hi>l.</hi> and no more: And then for Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, We Will and Command that the ſaid Treaſurer, Chancellor, and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:32072:31"/> of the Exchequer of Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors for the time being, make as haſty Proceſs as lawfully as may be made againſt the ſaid Barons of the ſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> and of the ſaid Towns of <hi>Rye</hi> and <hi>Winchelſea,</hi> and their Succeſſors for the levying of the ſaid 1000 Marks by them to Us, Our Heirs or Succeſſors to be forfeited for their exceeding the ſaid Sum of 500 <hi>l.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their ſaid Recognizance; And further for Us, Our Heirs and Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, We do Will and Charge all and every Collector and Collectors of Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors of every Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth to Us granted, or hereafter to Us, Our Heirs or Succeſſors to be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that they and every of them do receive of the ſaid Barons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> and of the ſaid Towns of <hi>Rye</hi> and <hi>Winchelſea,</hi> and their Succeſſors for them, their, and every of their Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and the Reſiants of the ſaid Ports, Towns, and Members, and the Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants of the ſaid Ports and Towns, all and every ſuch Bills and Billets as have been, or hereafter ſhall be tendred un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſaid Collector or Collectors, or any of them according to the purport and true meaning of theſe Preſents:
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:32072:31"/> And moreover for Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, of Our meer grace and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain knowledge, We do grant to the ſaid Barons of the ſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> and Towns of <hi>Rye</hi> and <hi>Winchelſea,</hi> and of the Members of the ſaid Ports and Towns and their Succeſſors, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they, nor their Succeſſors, nor any of them, nor the Reſiants of them, or any of them, nor the Advocants of the ſaid Ports and Towns, or any of them, or their Succeſſors, at any time hereafter by Us, Our Heirs or Succeſſors, or by the Treaſurer, Chancellor, or Barons of the ſaid Exchequer of Us, Our Heirs or Succeſſors, or by any Collectors, or other Officers or Miniſters of Us, Our Heirs or Succeſſors, ſhall be diſtreined, impeached, impleaded, or moleſted in any thing contrary to the Tenor and Purport of theſe Preſents, although ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs mention of the true yearly value or certainty of the Premiſes, or of any of them, or of any other Gifts or Grants by Us, or any of Our Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to the aforeſaid Barons of the ſaid <hi>Cinque Ports,</hi> or of the ſaid Towns of <hi>Rye</hi> and <hi>Winchelſea,</hi> and their Members heretofore made in theſe Preſents is not made, or any Statute, Act, Ordinance,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:32072:32"/> Proviſion, or Reſtraint to the contrary made, ordained or provided, or any other thing, cauſe or matter to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary in any wiſe notwithſtanding. In Witneſs whereof, We have cauſed theſe Our Letters to be made Patents.</p>
               <p>Witneſs Our Self at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the Six and twentieth day of <hi>January,</hi> in the Three and fortieth year of Our Reign.</p>
               <p>We have alſo looked upon the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Patents of Our moſt Dear Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father Lord <hi>James,</hi> late King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> made according to theſe Words: <hi>James</hi> by the Grace of God King of <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To all thoſe to whom theſe preſent Letters ſhall come, Greeting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In Witneſs whereof, We have cauſed theſe Our Letters to be made Patents.</p>
               <p>Witneſs Our Self at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the Thirtieth day of <hi>January,</hi> in the Second Year of Our Reign of <hi>England, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and of <hi>Scotland</hi> the Thirty eight.</p>
               <p>We have alſo looked upon the Letters Patents of Our moſt Dear Father Lord
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:32072:32"/> 
                  <hi>Charles,</hi> late King of <hi>England,</hi> (of Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Memory) made after theſe Words: <hi>Charles</hi> by the Grace of God of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> King, Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To all thoſe to whom theſe preſent Letters ſhall come, Greeting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In Witneſs whereof, We have cauſed theſe Our Letters to be made Patents.</p>
               <p>Witneſs Our Self at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the Sixteenth day of <hi>June,</hi> in the Tenth Year of Our Reign.</p>
               <p>Whereas Our Town and Port of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting</hi> in our County of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> and Our Town and Port of <hi>New-Romney,</hi> alias <hi>Romene,</hi> of <hi>Heeth, Dover,</hi> and <hi>Sand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich</hi> in Our County of <hi>Kent,</hi> are, and, from the time of the contrary of which, being never known to have been, were always the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> of Us and Our Progenitors, the Kings and Queens of <hi>England:</hi> And whereas alſo Our Towns of <hi>Rye</hi> and <hi>Winchelſea</hi> in Our ſaid County of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> are, and from the whole time aforeſaid have been Antient Towns, and within the Liberties of the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> aforeſaid: And whereas alſo the Town and Priviledged Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of <hi>Pevenſey,</hi> and the Town of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:32072:33"/> 
                  <hi>Seaford</hi> in the County of <hi>Suſſex</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; and the Towns and Places called <hi>Bulver-Heath, Little Iham,</hi> and <hi>Hidney</hi> in the County of <hi>Suſſex</hi> aforeſaid; and the Towns or Places called <hi>Beckesbourne,</hi> and <hi>Graunge,</hi> alias <hi>Grenche</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Kent</hi> aforeſaid, are and have been ever ſince the time aforenamed, Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the ſaid Town and Port of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting;</hi> And the Town of <hi>Bromhill</hi> in the aforeſaid Counties of <hi>Suſſex</hi> and <hi>Kent;</hi> and the Town of <hi>Lydd</hi> and <hi>Old-Romney</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent</hi> aforeſaid; and that other Towns or Places called <hi>Denge-Marſh, Oſwardſtone,</hi> alias <hi>Oſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent</hi> aforeſaid, are, and have been ever ſince the time aforenamed, Members of the ſaid Town and Port of <hi>New-Romney</hi> alias <hi>Romene;</hi> and alſo the Town of <hi>Weſtheeth</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent</hi> aforeſaid, is, and hath been ever ſince the time aforeſaid, a Member of the ſame Town and Port of <hi>Heeth;</hi> and alſo the Towns of <hi>Folk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone</hi> and <hi>Feverſham</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent</hi> aforeſaid; and the Towns and Places called <hi>Margate St. Johns, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſend, Brichington-Wood,</hi> alias <hi>Wood-Church,</hi> and <hi>St. Peters</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>Than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent</hi> aforeſaid;
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:32072:33"/> and <hi>Kingsdown,</hi> and <hi>Ringwolde</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent</hi> aforeſaid, are, and have been ever ſince the time aforeſaid, Members of the forenamed Town and Port of <hi>Dover;</hi> and alſo the Towns or Places of <hi>Fordwich, Deal, Walmer, Ramsgate,</hi> and <hi>Stomer</hi> in the aforeſaid County of <hi>Kent;</hi> and <hi>Sarr</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>Thannet</hi> in the ſaid County of <hi>Kent;</hi> and <hi>Brightlingſey</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> are, and have been from the whole time aforeſaid, Members of the ſaid Town and Port of <hi>Sandwich;</hi> as alſo the Town and Hundred of <hi>Tenderden</hi> in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid County of <hi>Kent,</hi> is a Member of the Antient Town of <hi>Rye:</hi> And whereas alſo the Barons and Inhabitants of the aforeſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, and Members of the ſame, and their Predeceſſors; and the Mayors, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>Haſting</hi> aforeſaid in the County of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> and their Predeceſſors; and the Mayors, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>New-Romney</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid in the ſaid County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and their Predeceſſors; and the Mayors, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>Heeth</hi> aforeſaid in the ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Kent,</hi> and their Predeceſſors; and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:32072:34"/> the Mayors, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>Dover</hi> aforeſaid, and their Predeceſſors; and the Mayors, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>Sandwich</hi> aforeſaid in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Kent,</hi> and their Predeceſſors; and the Mayors, Jurats, and Commons of the Antient Town of <hi>Rye</hi> aforeſaid in the County of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> and their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors; and the Mayors, Jurats, and Commons of the Ancient Town of <hi>Winchelſea</hi> aforeſaid in the County of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> and their Predeceſſors; and the Bayliff, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Priviledged Monaſtery of <hi>Pevenſey</hi> aforeſaid in the County of <hi>Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex,</hi> and their Predeceſſors; and the Bayliff, Jurats, and Commons of the Town of <hi>Seaford</hi> aforeſaid in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> and their Predeceſſors; and the Bayliff, Jurats, and Commons of the Town of <hi>Lydd</hi> aforeſaid in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and their Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors; and the Mayors, Jurats, and Commons of the Town of <hi>Folkſtone</hi> aforeſaid in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and their Predeceſſors; and the Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town of <hi>Feverſham</hi> aforeſaid in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and their Predeceſſors; and the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:32072:34"/> Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town of <hi>Fordwich</hi> aforeſaid in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and their Predeceſſors; and the Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Hundred of <hi>Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> aforeſaid in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and their Predeceſſors, have had, held, and enjoyed, and as yet have, hold, and enjoy divers Liberties, Franchiſes, Priviledges, Juriſdictions, Acquitances and Freedoms in time paſt, as well up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of the Letters Patents aforeſaid above recited, and ſeveral other Charters and Letters Patents by other Our Predeceſſors the Kings and Queens of <hi>England,</hi> to them and their Predeceſſors heretofore reſpectively gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, granted, and cofirmed; as upon the account of divers Preſcriptions and Cuſtoms uſed and accuſtomed in the ſame Ports, Towns, and Members re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively: We conſidering that the Barons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> aforeſaid, and the Barons of the Antient Towns of <hi>Rye</hi> and <hi>Winchelſea</hi> aforeſaid, and of the Members of the ſame Ports and Antient Towns, have from time to time throughly performed and paid great Services with their Navy to very many of Our Progenitors and Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:32072:35"/> the Kings and Queens of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to their great coſt, and to the great honour and profit of Our Progenitors and Our Kingdom aforeſaid: And gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly and piouſly conſidering that the ſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, and the Members of the ſame Ports and Towns are continually liable to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, Wrongs, Piracies, and ſudden Oppreſſions of Our Enemies: As alſo willing and greatly deſiring that the Navy of the Ports aforeſaid, and of the Antient Towns aforeſaid, and of the Members of the ſame Ports and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Towns ſhould not periſh or decay, (which cannot without great Charges and Expences be kept, maintained or furniſhed) but that it may be found fitter and in better readineſs to ſerve Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors: And that the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> and Antient Towns, and the Members of the ſame Ports and Antient Towns by the frequent recourſe and increaſe of Inhabitants may be made the ſtronger and better able to defend themſelves and the Neighbouring Country; And alſo Conſideration being had of the moſt pleaſing and accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Service which the Barons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> and of the Antient Towns
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:32072:35"/> aforeſaid have performed and paid to Us at Our Inauguration to the Crown of this Our Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as in times paſt they did, and were bound to do to Our Progenitors the Kings and Queens of <hi>England</hi> at their reſpective Coronation, the time of the contrary being never remembred to have been; and are ſtill bound to do to Our Heirs and Succeſſors the Kings of <hi>England</hi> at their Coronation ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Honour and Priviledge: And We have looked upon the ſeveral Letters Patents as well of Our Famous Predeceſſor aforeſaid the Lady <hi>Elizabeth</hi> late Queen of <hi>England,</hi> as of Our moſt Dear Grandfather aforeſaid, and Our moſt Dear Father abovementioned; and all and ſingular the things reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively contained and ſpecified in the ſame: As alſo all and ſingular the other Gifts, Grants, Charters, Confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Letters Patents whatſoever, made by one or more of Our Anceſtors or Predeceſſors the Kings or Queens of <hi>England</hi> to the Barons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> and to their Heirs and the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> or other Advocants of the Liberties of the ſame, and to the Barons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:32072:36"/> their Heirs and Succeſſors, and to the Barons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> and of the Members of the ſame, and to the Barons and Honeſt-Men of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> and of the Members of the ſame, and to the Mayor, Bailiffs, and Jurats of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> and Members of the ſame; and to the Mayor and Jurats, Bailiffs and Jurats, or Jurats of the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> and Members of the ſame, and every of them, and of any Port or Member aforeſaid: And to the Baron of the Town and Port of <hi>Haſting,</hi> and to the Bailiff, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>Haſting,</hi> and to the Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>Haſting;</hi> and to the Baron of the Town and Port of <hi>New-Romney,</hi> and to the Jurats and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>New-Romney,</hi> and to the Mayor, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>New-Romney;</hi> and to the Baron of the Town and Port of <hi>Heeth,</hi> and to the Jurats and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>Heeth,</hi> and to the Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>Heeth;</hi> and to the Baron of the Town and Port of <hi>Dover,</hi> and to the Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:32072:36"/> the Town and Port of <hi>Dover;</hi> and to the Baron of the Town and Port of <hi>Sandwi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h,</hi> and to the Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>Sandwich;</hi> and to the Baron of the Antient Town of <hi>Rye,</hi> and to the Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Antient Town of <hi>Rye;</hi> and to the Baron of the Antient Town of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelſea,</hi> and to the Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Antient Town of <hi>Winchelſea;</hi> and to the Baron of the Town and Priviledged Monaſtery of <hi>Pevenſey,</hi> and to the Bayliff, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Priviledged Monaſtery of <hi>Pevenſey;</hi> and to the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of the Town of <hi>Seaford,</hi> and to the Bayliff and Commons of the Town of <hi>Seaford;</hi> and to the Baron of the Town of <hi>Lydd,</hi> and to the Bayliff, Jurats, and Commons of the Town of <hi>Lydd;</hi> and to the Baron of the Town of <hi>Folkstone,</hi> and to the Mayor, Jurats, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the Town of <hi>Folkstone;</hi> and to the Baron of the Town of <hi>Feverſham,</hi> and to the Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town of <hi>Feverſham;</hi> and to the Baron of the Town of <hi>Fordwich,</hi> and to the Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town of <hi>Fordwich;</hi> and to the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:32072:37"/> of the Town and Hundred of <hi>Tenterden,</hi> and to the Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of <hi>Tenterden;</hi> by whatſoever Names or Name, or by whatſoever in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporations or incorporation, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of incorporation hitherto they have been, or now, and for the future ſhall be known, called or named; And We Warranting to them, and making them well-liking to Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, as much as in Us lieth, all and ſingular their Liberties, Priviledes, Franchiſes, Cuſtoms, Freedoms, Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitances, Exemptions, Juriſdictions, Fairs, Markets, Marts, Toll, Stallage, Piccage, Cuſtom, Eaſments, Fines, Amercements, and other Profits and Hereditaments contained and ſpecified in the ſaid Letters Patents, or in any one or more of them, (by theſe Preſents in no wiſe to be recalled, diminiſhed, or changed) do Ratifie, Approve, Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of, and Confirm them by theſe Preſents, as they have hitherto reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably uſed them: And further of Our more free and ſpecial Grace, certain Knowledge and meer Motion, We have given, granted and confirmed, and by theſe Preſents for Us, Our Heirs and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:32072:37"/> Succeſſors, do give, grant, and confirm to the aforenamed Barons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> and the Antient Towns aforeſaid, and of the Members of the ſame Ports and Towns, and their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting</hi> in the County of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> and to their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>New-Romney</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and to their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>Heeth</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and to their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>Dover</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and to their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>Sandwich</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and to their Succeſſors; and to the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Antient Town of <hi>Rye</hi> in the County of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> and their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the Antient Town of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelſea</hi> in the County of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> and their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Bayliff,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:32072:38"/> Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Priviledged Monaſtery of <hi>Pevenſey</hi> in the County of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors; and to the aforeſaid Bayliff, Jurats, and Commons of the Town of <hi>Seaford</hi> in the County of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> and their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Bayliff, Jurats, and Commons of the Town of <hi>Lydd</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and their Succeſſors; and to the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town of <hi>Folkstone</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the Town of <hi>Feverſham</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town of <hi>Fordwich</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats, and Commons of the Town and Hundred of <hi>Tenterden</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and their Succeſſors, reſpectively: That every Mayor, and Jurat of every reſpective Port of the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, and their Succeſſors reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, within every Port aforeſaid, for every Port aforeſaid, and for all other Places or Towns whatſoever, or any other Place and Town whatſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:32072:38"/> to any Port aforeſaid, or being a Member of any Port aforeſaid, which have not within their ſelves or ſelf a Mayor or Bayliff elected by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of thoſe places or place, Towns or Town: And alſo that every Mayor and Jurat of every of the Antient Towns aforeſaid, and their Succeſſors reſpectively; and every Mayor of the aforeſaid Town of <hi>Feverſham,</hi> and their Succeſſors reſpectively; and every May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or and Jurat of every of the other Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Ports and Antient Towns aforeſaid where there is a Mayor and Jurats, and their Succeſſors reſpectively, within every Antient Town, and within the aforeſaid Town of <hi>Feverſham,</hi> and within every other Member of the Ports and Antient Towns aforeſaid, for every of the Antient Towns afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and for the aforeſaid Town of <hi>Feverſham,</hi> and for every other Member aforeſaid reſpectively; and every Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff and Jurat, and every Bayliff where there is no Jurat of every Member of the Ports aforeſaid where ſuch Bayliff is choſen by the Commons of the ſame Member, and their Succeſſors reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, within every other Member of the Ports aforeſaid, for every ſuch Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:32072:39"/> as above ſeverally and reſpectively limited, may for the future for ever have and hold, and have power to have and to hold before the ſame Mayor and Jurats, and Mayor, and Bayliff, and Jurats, and Bayliff reſpectively within every ſuch Port of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, and Members afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, at ſome moſt convenient place, days, and accuſtomed times there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively, one Court of Record: And that the ſame Mayors and Jurats, and Mayors, Bayliffs, and Jurats, and Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffs and their Succeſſors reſpectively, may and ſhall have in every Court of the ſaid Courts ſeverally and reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, more fully and freely than they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly had in the ſame, full Power and Authority by theſe Preſents of hearing and determining in the ſeveral Courts aforeſaid reſpectively by ſome grievance in the ſame to be conſidered, and of holding all and ſingular the Suits of and concerning all and all manner of Debts, Accounts, Covenants, Contracts, Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanors by Force and Arms, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe done in contempt of Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors; detaining of Goods, Contempts, Cheatings, Writs of Withernam; and of and concerning
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:32072:39"/> all and all manner of other Actions,<note place="margin">All Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal and mixt.</note> Real, Perſonal, and Mixt whatſoever; Suits of Aſſize of Freſh Diſſeiſin, or of the Death of an Anceſtor, or of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſeiſin within every ſuch Port, and Bounds, Limits, and Precincts of the ſame Port, or any other places or place, Towns or Town appertaining or belonging to any Port aforeſaid, or being a Member of any ſuch Port or Ports where neither Mayor nor Bayliff is elected reſpectively; and within every Antient Town aforeſaid, and within the aforeſaid Town of <hi>Fever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham,</hi> and within every other Member aforeſaid, and the Bounds, Limits, and Precincts of every ſuch Antient Towns, and of the Town of <hi>Feverſham</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and other Suits which any way happen or ſhall happen, chance or ſhall chance to be within any other Members aforeſaid, reſpectively: And that the ſame Mayors and Jurats, and Mayors, and Bayliffs, and Jurats, and Jurats and Bayliffs, and their Succeſſors reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, may upon all ſuch Pleas, Actions, Complaints of Aſſize of freſh Diſſeiſin, or of the Death of an Anceſtor, or of Rediſſeiſin in the ſaid Courts, or any of them which are, or ſhall be moved
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:32072:40"/> or redreſſed, have Power, Authority, and Licenſe to bring and force the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or Perſons againſt whom any ſuch Pleas, Actions, or Complaints of Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſize of Freſh Diſſeiſin, or of the Death of an Anceſtor, or of Rediſſeiſin which ſhall happen to be moved or redreſſed in the Courts aforeſaid, or any of them, to appear to the Suit by the Summons, At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachments, or Diſtraint of the Sergeant of the Mace to the Mayors and Jurats, and Mayors, and Bayliffs, and Jurats, and Bayliffs of every Port, Antient Town, and Member of the Ports and Antient Towns aforeſaid, or any of the ſame reſpectively; or by any other Officers who are or ſhall be deputed by them reſpectively for the ſame, or by any other Officers to be deputed by the aforeſaid Courts or any of them; or by an Attachment of the Body of the Perſon or Perſons by any ſuch Sergeants of the Mace, or other Officers to be Executed according to the Law and Cuſtom of Our Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> or the Cuſtom of any Port or Antient Town aforeſaid, or of any Member of the Ports and Antient Towns aforeſaid reſpectively, or according to the Cuſtom uſed in any of our Burroughs or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:32072:40"/> within Our Kingdom of <hi>England:</hi> And to hear and determine all and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular the Pleas, Actions, Plaints, and Aſſize of Freſh Diſſeiſin, of the Death of an Anceſtor, or Rediſſeiſin in any one of the Courts aforeſaid reſpectively; and to bring and determine them by ſuch like Proceedings, Conſiderations, Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Executions of Judgments, by which they bring and determine ſuch like Pleas, Actions, Plaints of Aſſize of Freſh Diſſeiſin, of the Death of an Anceſtor, or of Rediſſeiſin according to the Law of Our Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> in any of Our Courts, or according to the Cuſtom in any of the Antient Towns aforeſaid belonging to any ſuch Port, or in any Member of the Ports and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Towns aforeſaid reſpectively, or in any Burrough, or County, or Liberty within the ſaid Kingdom of <hi>England;</hi> Or they may be brought and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined at the pleaſure of the Mayors and Jurats, Mayor, Bayliff, and Jurats, and Bayliff reſpectively, and make and execute the Executions, Proceſſes, and Judgments thereupon by the aforeſaid Sergeant of the Mace, or any other Officer aforeſaid: And that every May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, Jurat, and Commons of any of the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:32072:41"/> 
                  <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers aforeſaid whatſoever, where there is a Mayor, and their Succeſſors reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively; and all Bayliffs, Jurats, and Commons, and the Bayliffs and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of every Member of the Ports aforeſaid, where the ſaid Bayliffs are elected by the Commons of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers aforeſaid, and their Succeſſors, may and ſhall have and receive to their own proper uſe and advantage reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, all and ſingular the Fines, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercements, Ranſoms, Iſſues, Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and other Profits whatſoever, coming, riſing, chancing, or happening from and in the Courts aforeſaid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively: And that they may by their Officers levy, receive, ſeize, and keep all and ſingular thoſe Fines, Ranſoms, Amercements, Iſſues, Forfeitures, and Profits for their own proper uſe and advantage reſpectively from time to time, by an Action or Actions of Debt, or ſuch other Suits, Actions, Means, Ways, and Proceedings to be had and proſecuted in any Court or Courts of Record within the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> or Antient Towns aforeſaid, or Members of the ſame aforeſaid, or in any one or more of them, by which ſuch like Fines,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:32072:41"/> Amercements, Ranſoms, Iſſues, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures, and Profits are wont to be le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied, received, and recovered in any of the Courts of Us, Our Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, throughout Our whole Kingdom of <hi>England;</hi> or may be without the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment of Us, Our Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, or of any of Our Officers who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever: And moreover for the better ruling and governing of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, and Members aforeſaid, We of Our ſpecial Grace, certain knowledge, and meer motion have given, granted, and confirmed, and by theſe Preſents for Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, do give, grant and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm to the ſaid Barons and honeſt Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> and Antient Towns aforeſaid, and to the Members of the ſame Ports and Towns, and to their Succeſſors, and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>Haſting</hi> in the County of <hi>Suſſex</hi> and their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the Town and Port of <hi>New-Romney</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent</hi> and their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>Heeth</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:32072:42"/> and their Succeſſors; and to the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>Dover</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>Sand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Antient Town of <hi>Rye</hi> in the County of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> and their Succeſſors; And to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Town of <hi>Winchelſea</hi> in the County of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> and their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Bayliff, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Priviledged Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Pevenſey</hi> in the County of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> and their Succeſſors; and to the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Bayliff, Jurats, and Commons of the Town of <hi>Seaford</hi> in the County of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> and their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Bayliff, Jurats, and Commons of the Town of <hi>Lydd</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats and Commons of the Town of <hi>Folkstone</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the Town of <hi>Feverſham</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and their Succeſſors;
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:32072:42"/> and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town of <hi>Fordwich</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats, and Commons of the Town and Hundred of <hi>Tenterden</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and their <hi>Succeſſors</hi> reſpectively; That every Mayor and Jurat of every Port of the aforeſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively within the Ports aforeſaid, and the Bounds, Limits, and Precincts of the ſame Ports, as alſo within all other Places and Towns, or any other Place and Town appertaining or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to any Port aforeſaid, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Member of any Port aforeſaid, in which Places or Towns, or in which Place or Town the Mayor or Bayliff is not choſe by the Commons of thoſe Places or Towns, or Place or Town, and their Succeſſors reſpectively: And every Mayor and Jurat of either of the aforeſaid Antient Towns of <hi>Rye</hi> and <hi>Winchelſea,</hi> and any Member of the Ports and Antient Towns aforeſaid, where there is a Mayor, and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors reſpectively: As alſo every Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff and Jurat of any Member of the Ports aforeſaid, where ſuch Bayliff is choſen by the Commons of the ſame
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:32072:43"/> Member, and their Succeſſors reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, within the Antient Towns and Members aforeſaid, and the Bounds, Limits, and Precincts of the ſame, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally, according as it is before limited, may and ſhall be henceforward for ever Keepers of the Peace,<note place="margin">Keepers of the Peace.</note> and Juſtices to Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, to keep the Peace for Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors; and that every of them may and ſhall be Keeper of the Peace, and Juſtice to Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, to keep the Peace for Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, within each of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, Members, and Places above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named, and the Bounds and Precincts of the ſame, and every of them ſeverally and reſpectively: And We do create, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point, make, ordain and confirm by theſe Preſents the ſaid Mayors, Bayliffs, and Jurats, and every of them, and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors reſpectively, Keepers of the Peace and Juſtices to Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, to keep the Peace for Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, within every of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, Members and Places aforeſaid, and the Liberties, Bounds, Limits and Precincts of the ſame reſpectively; And We ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point them to keep, and cauſe to be
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:32072:43"/> kept all Ordinances and Statutes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſet forth, or hereafter to be ſet forth, for the good of the Peace of Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, and for the preſervation of the ſame, and for the quiet rule and government of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple belonging to Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, in all and ſingular their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, within every of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, Members, and Places aforeſaid, and the Liberties, Bounds, Limits, and Precincts of the ſame ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally and reſpectively, according to the force, tenor, and effect of the ſame: And to Correct and Puniſh all Offenders againſt the form of the ſaid Ordinances and Statutes, or any of them, in that place reſpectively, as according to the form of thoſe Ordinances and Statutes they were enjoyn'd to do: And to make to appear before the aforeſaid Mayor, Bayliff, and Jurats reſpectively, all thoſe who have threatned any miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief to the Perſons of any of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of Us, Our Heirs or Succeſſors, or to Fire their Houſes; and make them bring ſufficient ſecurity for their peace and good behaviour toward Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, and toward the Subjects of Us, Our Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:32072:44"/> and if they refuſe to find out ſuch Security, then to cauſe them to be kept ſafe in Priſon until they ſhall find ſuch Security: And moreover We Will, and for Us, Our Heirs and Succceſſors, by theſe Preſents do grant and confirm to the aforeſaid Mayors, Jurats, and Commons; to the Bayliffs, Jurats, and Commons; and to the Bayliffs and Commons of every of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, and Members afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and to their Succeſſors reſpectively, That any two or more of the aforeſaid Mayors and Jurats of any Port of the aforeſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors reſpectively, within the Ports aforeſaid, and the Liberties, Bounds, Limits, and Precincts of the ſame, as alſo within any other Place or Places, Town or Towns, appertaining or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to any Port aforeſaid, or being a Member of any Port aforeſaid, in which Place or Places, Town or Towns, Mayor nor Bayliff is choſen by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the ſaid Place or Places, Town or Towns; (the Mayor of which Places or his Deputy for the time being We Will always have to be but one) and that any two or more of the aforeſaid Mayors and Jurats of any of the aforeſaid An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:32072:44"/> Towns of <hi>Rye</hi> and <hi>Winchelſea,</hi> and of any Member aforeſaid of the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> and Antient Towns aforeſaid where there ſhall be a Mayor, and their Succeſſors reſpectively; (the Mayor of which Places or his Deputy for the time being We Will always have to be but one) and that any two or more of the aforeſaid Bayliffs and Jurats of any Member of the Ports aforeſaid where ſuch Bayliff is choſen by the Commons of the ſaid Member, and their Succeſſors re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively; (the Bayliff of which Place or his Deputy for the time being, We will always have to be but one) within the Antient Towns and Members afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and the Liberties, Bounds, Limits, and Precincts of the ſame ſeverally and reſpectively, for the future may and ſhall be for ever Juſtices to Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors; and henceforward may for ever have full Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to make enquiry, under the Oath of the honeſt and lawful Inhabitants of the aforeſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, and Members of the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively by whom the truth of the matter may be the better known,<note place="margin">Felony, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to hear and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.</note> after all and all manner of Felony, Murder, Manſlaughter, Witchcrafts, Art-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:32072:45"/> Treſpaſſes, Foreſtallers, Regra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, Ingroſſers, and Extortions what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, and of all and ſingular other Miſdemeanors and Offences concerning which the Juſtices of the Peace to Us, Our Heirs or Succeſſors lawfully may or ought to make enquiry within the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, and Members of the ſame, or within any of them, or within any County of Our Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> by whomſoever or howſoever they have been done or committed within any of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, Members and Places aforeſaid, and the Liberties, Bounds, Limits, and Precincts of the ſame ſeverally and reſpectively, or which ſhall hereafter happen to be done or attempted in the ſame Places reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively; As alſo after all thoſe who within the Antient Towns, Members, and Places aforeſaid of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> or within the Liberties, Bounds, Limits, and Precincts of the ſame reſpectively, have aſſembled together againſt the Peace of Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, to the diſturbance of the Subjects of Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, or by force went or rode about Armed, or for the future ſhall preſume ſo to go or ride:
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:32072:45"/> And alſo after all thoſe who have lien in wait to maim or kill any of the Nation of Us, Our Heirs or Succeſſors, or for the future ſhall preſume to lie in wait; as alſo after all Inn-Keepers, and all and ſingular thoſe Perſons who have offended or done any thing againſt the form of the Ordinances and Statutes or any of them, which are or ſhall be put forth for the common good of Our Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> or the Subjects of Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, by the abuſe of Weights or Meaſures, or in the ſelling of Victuals, or for the time to come ſhall preſume ſo to offend or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any ſuch thing within the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, Members, or Places aforeſaid, or within the Liberties, Bounds, Limits, and Precincts of the ſame reſpectively; and alſo after all Conſtables whatſoever, Petty-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables, Keepers of Gaols, and other Officers and Miniſters, who in the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of their Offices have carried themſelves unſeemly concerning the things aforementioned or any of them, or for the future ſhall preſume to carry themſelves unſeemly, or have been cold, remiſs, or negligent in the Execution of their Offices, or for the future ſhall
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:32072:46"/> be, within the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, Members or Places aforeſaid, or within the Liberties, Bounds, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, and Precincts of the ſame reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively; and to make enquiry more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly about the truth of all and ſingular the Articles, Circumſtances, and other things whatſoever by whomſoever, and by what mean ſoever the things aforementioned or any thing that concerns them are done or committed, or which for the future ſhall happen there reſpectively to be done or attempted within the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, Members or Places aforeſaid, or within the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Bounds, Limits, and Precincts of the ſame reſpectively; and for the look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after all Indictments whatſoever which have been or ſhall be ſo preſented before the aforeſaid Mayors and Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffs or their Deputies, and the Jurats and their Succeſſors reſpectively, or which have been made or exhibited, and not yet determined, before o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Our late Juſtices of the Peace, within the aforeſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Towns, and the Members of the ſame, or any of them reſpectively; and for the directing, making, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing Proceſs againſt all and ſingular
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:32072:46"/> of them ſo indicted, or againſt thoſe who for the time to come ſhall happen to be indicted before the aforeſaid Mayor or his Deputy and Jurats, the Bayliff or his Deputy and Jurats, or their Succeſſors reſpectively, or againſt thoſe who ſhall render or give up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to their own proper Officers; and to hear and determine all and ſingular the Felonies, Murders, Manſlaughters, Witchcrafts, Inchantments, Fortune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telling, Art-magick, Treſpaſſes, Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtallers, Regrators, Ingroſſers, Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Aſſemblings, Indictments afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and all and ſingular the reſt above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, according to the Laws and Statutes of Our Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> which are already ſet forth or ſhall be ſet forth; and to correct and puniſh the ſaid Delinquents and every of them for their Offences, by Fines, Ranſoms, Amercements, Forfeitures, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way as hath been uſed, or ought, or hereafter ſhall be, to be done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law and Cuſtom of Our Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> or according to the Form of the Ordinances and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes aforeſaid already ſet forth or hereafter to be ſet forth; and to do, execute and perform all other things,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:32072:47"/> within the aforeſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Towns, and Members of the ſame, and the Liberties, Bounds, Limits, and Precincts of the ſame reſpectively as fully, freely, and perfectly, and in as ample manner and form, as the Juſtices of the Peace of Us, Our Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors in the Counties of <hi>Kent, Suſſex,</hi> and <hi>Eſſex,</hi> or in any of them, or in any other County within Our Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> have heretofore done, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and executed, or may or ſhall hereafter have power to do, perform, or execute by virtue of any Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Act of Parliament, Statute, Law, or Cuſtom, or by other legal way what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, and in as ample manner and form, as if all thoſe things had been exactly and by ſpecial words contained, declared, repeated, and expreſſed in theſe Our Letters Patents: And that any two or more of the aforeſaid Mayors and Jurats of any Port of the aforeſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors reſpectively, within the Ports aforeſaid, and within the Liberties, Bounds, Limits and Precincts of the ſame, as alſo within any other Place or Places, Town or Towns whatſoever appertaining or belonging to any Port
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:32072:47"/> aforeſaid, or being a Member of any Port aforeſaid, in which Place or Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Town or Towns the Mayor or Bayliff is not choſen by the Commons of the ſaid Place or Places, Town or Towns, (the Mayor of which Places and his Deputy for the time being, We Will always have to be but one) and that any two or more of the aforeſaid Mayors and Jurats, and their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors reſpectively, of either of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Towns of <hi>Rye</hi> and <hi>Winchelſea</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, and of any Member of the aforeſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> and Antient Towns aforeſaid where there is a Mayor; (the Mayor of which Places or his Deputy for the time being, We Will always have to be but one) and any two or more of the aforeſaid Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffs and Jurats of any Member of the Ports aforeſaid where ſuch Bayliff is choſen by the Commons of the ſame Member, and their Succeſſors reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, (the Bayliff of which Place or his Deputy for the time being, We Will always have to be but one) from time to time for ever for the future may and ſhall be the Juſtices of Us,<note place="margin">Juſtices to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Gaols.</note> Our Heirs and Succeſſors to deliver Gaols from the Priſons lying and being in the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:32072:48"/> ſame, within the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, Members, and other Places aforeſaid, and within the Liberties, Bounds, Limits, and Precincts of the ſame reſpectively, from time to time acccording to the Laws and Cuſtom of this Our Kingdom of <hi>England:</hi> And by theſe Preſents we create, appoint, make, ordain, and confirm any two or more of the ſaid Mayors, Bayliffs, and Jurats, and their Succeſſors reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (the Mayor and Bayliff of which Places or their Deputy, We Will always have to be but one) the Juſtices of Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors to deliver Gaols from the Priſons being in the ſame, within the aforeſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, Members, and Places aforeſaid, and within the Bounds, Limits, Liberties, and Precincts of the ſame reſpectively from time to time ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Cuſtom of this Kingdom of <hi>England;</hi> and to do, execute, and perform all other things whatſoever, from time to time, within the aforeſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and Places aforeſaid, and within the Bounds, Limits, Liberties, and Precincts of the ſame reſpectively, as fully, freely, and compleatly, and in
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:32072:48"/> as ample manner and form,<note place="margin">In as am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and form as other Juſtices.</note> as the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors in the aforeſaid Counties of <hi>Kent, Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex,</hi> and <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and any one of them, or in any other County within the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> have heretofore done, performed, or executed to the delivering Gaols, by virtue of any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, Act of Parliament, Statute, Law, or Cuſtom, or any other legal way whatſoever, or for the future may or ſhall have the Power to do, perform, and execute; and in as ample manner and form as if all thoſe things had been exactly and by ſpecial words contained, declared, repeated, and expreſſed in theſe Our Letters Patents: And that no other Juſtices of Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, that are appointed or are to be appointed for the Peace of Us, Our Heirs, or Succeſſors, within the aforeſaid Counties of <hi>Kent, Suſſex,</hi> and <hi>Eſſex,</hi> or any of them; Nor any Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, appointed or to be appointed to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire after, hear, and determine divers Felonies, Treſpaſſes, and other Miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanors, or to deliver Gaols, within the aforeſaid Counties of <hi>Kent, Suſſex,</hi> and <hi>Eſſex,</hi> or any of them; Nor any
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:32072:49"/> Sheriff, Under-Sheriff, Coroner, Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheator, nor any other Officers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to Us,<note place="margin">No o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices may be ſuffered to enter in, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> Our Heirs or Succeſſors, within the aforeſaid Counties of <hi>Kent, Suſſex,</hi> and <hi>Eſſex,</hi> or any one of them for the future enter or come in any wiſe to do, act, or perform any thing or things within the aforeſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, Members or Places aforeſaid, or within the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Bounds, Limits, or Precincts of the ſame; Nor may any of them have or exerciſe any Authority or Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on concerning any cauſes, things, or matters whatſoever, any way apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining, belonging, or lying upon, or which for the future ſhall happen to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertain, belong, or lie upon the Juſtices of Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed or to be appointed to keep the Peace, or to enquire after, hear, and determine divers Felonies, Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, and other Miſdemeanors, or to deliver Gaols, within the ſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, Members, and Places aforeſaid, or within the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Bounds, Limits, and Precincts of the ſame, or any of them, at what time or upon what cauſe ſoever thoſe things ſhall chance or happen to be: And that
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:32072:49"/> every Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of every of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, and Members aforeſaid where there is a Mayor, and their Succeſſors reſpectively; and every Bayliff, Jurats, and Commons; and Bayliff and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of every of the Members of the Ports aforeſaid, where ſuch Bayliff is choſen by the Commons of the Members aforeſaid, and their Succeſſors reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively,<note place="margin">All Fines, Iſſues, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> may and ſhall have and receive to their own proper uſe and advantage reſpectively, all and all manner of Fines, Iſſues, Ranſoms, Amercements, Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and Profits whatſoever, which ſhall from time to time for ever for the future be ſeized, forfeited, adjudged, come, happen, or fall out before the abovenam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Juſtices of Us, Our Heirs and Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, that are to keep the Peace, and alſo thoſe that are to enquire after, hear, and determine divers Felonies, Treſpaſſes, and other Miſdemeanors, or thoſe that deliver Gaols belonging to Us, Our Heirs or Succeſſors, within the ſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and Places aforeſaid, or before any one of thoſe whoſoever reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and that they may levy and receive all thoſe things by their own proper
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:32072:50"/> and ſeveral Officers, for their own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per uſe reſpectively, without any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction from thence to be made to the Exchequer of Us, Our Heirs or Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors; and without the impediment of Us,<note place="margin">Without any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction from thence to Our Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And without impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> Our Heirs or Succeſſors, or Our Miniſters whoſoever: Notwithſtanding We Will, and Our intent is, and by theſe Preſents We grant and confirm for Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, to the aforeſaid Mayors, Jurats, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; Bayliffs, Jurats, and Commons; and Bayliffs and Commons of every Port, Antient Towns aforeſaid, and the Members aforeſaid, and to their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors reſpectively, That every Mayor, Bayliff, and Jurat aforeſaid, who now is, or hereafter ſhall be reſpectively, before that he or they be admitted to the executing the Office of a Juſtice of Peace within any of the aforeſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, Members or Places aforeſaid, or within the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, Bounds, Limits, or Precincts of the ſame reſpectively, by virtue of theſe Our Letters Patents,<note place="margin">An Oath to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form and execute the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</note> or of the aforeſaid Letters Patents of Our ſaid moſt Dear Grandfather <hi>James,</hi> ſhall and may from time to time take ſuch a Corporal Oath upon the Sacred Goſpel
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:32072:50"/> of God, faithfully to execute that Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in all things and through all things according as he ſhall be Conſtituted and Ordained by the Laws and Ordinances made for that purpoſe by the above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Mayor, Jurats, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; Bayliff, Jurats, and Commons; and Bayliff and Commons of every of the Ports, Antient Towns, and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers aforeſaid, and their Succeſſors re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively, or the major part of them, without any other Warrant, Writ, or Commiſſion to be procured or obtained from Us, Our Heirs or Suceſſors, <hi>viz.</hi> That every Mayor and Bayliff afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, who now is or hereafter ſhall be reſpectively, may and ſhall from time to time take ſuch an Oath as it is above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, before the aforeſaid Jurats, or any two or more of them reſpectively, who now are or hereafter ſhall be; and that every of the aforeſaid Jurats who now is or hereafter ſhall be, ſhall and may from time to time take that Oath as it is aforeſaid, before the aforeſaid Mayors and Bayliffs who now are or hereafter ſhall be reſpectively, without any other Warrant, Writ or Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to be procured or obtained from Us, Our Heirs or Succeſſors; (to which</p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:32072:51"/>
            </div>
            <div n="100-121" type="part">
               <p> Mayors, Jurats, and Commons; Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff, Jurats, and Commons; Bayliff and Commons of every of the Ports, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Towns, and Members aforeſaid, and to their Succeſſors reſpectively, We give and grant by theſe Preſents for Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, full Power and Authority to ordain and make the ſaid Laws and Ordinances from time to time.) And moreover We Will, and by theſe Preſents do give, grant, and confirm for Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, to the ſame Mayor, Jurats, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; Bayliff, Jurats, and Commons; and Bayliff and Commons of every of the Ports, Antient Towns, and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers aforeſaid, and to their Succeſſors reſpectively, That the aforeſaid Mayors, Bayliffs, and Jurats who now are, or hereafter ſhall be reſpectively, ſhall for the future from time to time for ever have full Power and Authority of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtring ſuch an Oath, as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, to all and ſingular Perſons who are, or hereafter ſhall be choſen into the Office of a Mayor, Bayliff, or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, or the Members aforeſaid, or of any one or more of them reſpectively, without any other or further Warrant,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:32072:51"/> Writ or Commiſſion to be had or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured for that purpoſe from Us, Our Heirs or Succeſſors: And further We Will, and by theſe Preſents do grant for Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, to the abovementioned Mayor, Jurats, and Commons; Bayliff, Jurats, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; and Bayliff and Commons of every of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, and Members of the ſame, and to their Succeſſors reſpectively, That if it ſhall happen that any Mayor of any Port, or of any Antient Town, or of a Member of the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> and Antient Towns aforeſaid where there is a Mayor for the time being; Or that any Bayliff of any Member of the Ports aforeſaid, for the time being, ſhould hereafter be in ſuch a manner troubled with Sickneſs, or any other infirmity for ſome time or times, or by ſome other cauſe juſt and reaſonable be ſo detained or made unfit, that he or they cannot at preſent look to the Offices of Mayor, and Bayliff, and the neceſſary buſineſſes thereunto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing; Or that for any reaſonable cauſe he ſhould go out of the Ports, Antient Towns, and Members afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; That then and ſo often, it may
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:32072:52"/> and ſhall be lawful for any ſuch Mayor and Bayliff of any of the aforeſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, and Members of the ſame for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſpectively, to make and appoint any one Jurat of the ſaid Port, Antient Town, and Member aforeſaid reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively where the ſaid Mayor or Bayliff for the time being was, to be the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty of the ſaid Mayor or Bayliff be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as is aforeſaid, troubled with Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or any infirmity, or upon ſome reaſonable account, abſent, detained, or made unfit,<note place="margin">A Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to be made for a Mayor or Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l ff.</note> as 'tis aboveſaid; Which Deputy put in the Office of the Mayor, or Bayliff aforeſaid, ſo made and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, may and ſhall be the Deputy of the ſaid Mayor or Bayliff reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from time to time, as often as the aforeſaid Mayor or Bayliff reſpectively ſhall happen to be ſo troubled with Sickneſs or any infirmity, or upon any other reaſonable account be detained or made unfit, or be abſent as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; and may continue Deputy all the time the aforeſaid Mayor or Bayliff ſhall continue in the Office of Mayor or Bayliff reſpectively, unleſs in the mean time the aforeſaid Mayor or Bayliff ſhall make or appoint another Jurat of
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:32072:52"/> the ſaid Port, Antient Town, or Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber aforeſaid reſpectively, his Deputy: And that every ſuch Deputy of the aforeſaid Mayor or Bayliff ſo made and appointed as is aforementioned, may by virtue of theſe Our Letters Patents do and execute all and ſingular of thoſe things which do or may belong to the Office of a Mayor or Bayliff reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which are to be done and executed from time to time as often as the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Mayor or Bayliff reſpectively ſhall ſo happen to be troubled with Sickneſs or any infirmity, or be detained, made unfit, or be abſent; during ſuch time as the aforeſaid Deputy of the ſaid Mayor or Bayliff ſhall be and continue, as fully, freely, and entirely, and may in as ample manner and form do and execute them as if the Mayor or Bayliff aforeſaid were preſent, (a Corporal Oath upon the Sacred Goſpel of God for the good and faithful performance of all and ſingular the things which belong to the Office of a Deputy of the Mayor or Bayliff aforeſaid, being firſt taken by ſuch a Deputy, before one or more of the other Jurats aforeſaid of the Port, Antient Town, or Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber aforeſaid reſpectively) and as often
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:32072:53"/> as ſuch a chance ſhall ſo happen: And moreover We Will, and by theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents do grant and confirm for Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, to the ſame May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, Jurats, and Commons; Bayliff, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats, and Commons; and Bayliff and Commons of every Port, Antient Town, and Member aforeſaid, and to their Succeſſors reſpectively, That every ſuch one or more of the Jurats may from time to time for the future have full power and authority of giving and adminiſtring ſuch Corporal Oath upon the Sacred Goſpel of God, as is aboveſaid, to every Deputy of a Mayor or Bayliff in ſuch a caſe as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned to be appointed, without any further Writ, Commiſſion or fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Warrant to be procured or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained upon that account from Us, Our Heirs or Succeſſors: And further, That the Barons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> aforeſaid, and Antient Towns of <hi>Rye</hi> and <hi>Winchelſea</hi> aforeſaid, and of the Members of the ſame Ports and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Towns, may the more commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly perform the Service of their Ships aforeſaid to Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors at fit times; As alſo for the better rule, government, and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:32072:53"/> of the aforeſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> and the aforeſaid Antient Towns, and Members o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> every of the ſame <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> and Antient Towns, We do grant and confirm to the ſame Barons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> and Antient Towns afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and of the Members of the ſame Ports and Towns, and to their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cceſſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>Haſting,</hi> and their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>New-Romney,</hi> and their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>Heeth,</hi> and their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the Town and Port of <hi>Dover,</hi> and their Succeſſors; and to the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>Sandwich,</hi> and their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Antient Town of <hi>Rye,</hi> and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Antient Town of <hi>Winchelſea,</hi> and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors; and to the aforeſaid Bayliff, Jurats, and Commons of the Town
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:32072:54"/> and Priviledged Monaſtery of <hi>Pevenſey,</hi> and their Succeſſors; and to the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Bayliff, Jurats, and Commons of the Town of <hi>Seaford,</hi> and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors; and to the aforeſaid Bayliff, Jurats, and Commons of the Town of <hi>Lydd,</hi> and their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the Town of <hi>Folkſtone,</hi> and their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town of <hi>Feverſham,</hi> and their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats, and Commons of the Town of <hi>Fordwich,</hi> and their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the Town and Hundred of <hi>Tenterden,</hi> and their Succeſſors, for the maintaining and preſerving the Service of their Navy aforeſaid to be perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Us, Our Heirs or Succeſſors; or for the defending and maintaining the Liberty of Franchiſes, Cuſtoms, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, and Burdens of every Port and Antient Town aforeſaid, and of every Member of the Ports and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Towns aforeſaid reſpectively; as alſo for the maintaining all Neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Offices whatſoever of every Port and Antient Town, and of every
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:32072:54"/> Member of the Ports and Antient Towns aforeſaid, or any of them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively, according to the above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned limitation; That every Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Port of the aforeſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> reſpectively, may in and upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and all other Inhabitants and Reſiants whatſoever, within every ſuch Port, the Bounds, Limits, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cincts of the ſame Port, and within any other Place or Places, Town or Towns whatſoever belonging to any Port aforeſaid, or being a Member of any ſuch Port, and not having within themſelves a Mayor or Bayliff choſen by the Commons of the ſame Place or Places, as is aboveſaid; and upon all and ſingular Land-rents and Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances whatſoever, within any of thoſe Ports, the Bounds, Limits, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cincts of the ſame, and within any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Place or Places, Town or Towns belonging to any of the Ports afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, or being a Member of any Port not having a Mayor or Bayliff elected reſpectively, as is abovementioned: And upon all and ſingular the Goods, Chattels, and Merchandiſes of all and ſingular the Inhabitants and Reſiants,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:32072:55"/> whether Poſſeſſors or Tenants of any ſuch Lands or Inheritances whatſoever within any ſuch Port, the Liberties, Limits, and Precincts of the ſame, and within any other Place or Places, Town or Towns belonging to any Port afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, or being a Member of any ſuch Port not having within themſelves a Mayor or Bayliff elected reſpectively, as is aforementioned; and every May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, Jurats, and Commons of any of the Antient Towns aforeſaid, and of any Member of the Ports and Antient Towns aforeſaid where there is a Mayor reſpectively, may in and upon themſelves, and upon any others of the Inhabitants and Reſiants within any ſuch Antient Town, the Liberties, Limits, and Precincts of the ſame, and within any ſuch Member, the Bounds, Limits, and Precincts of the ſame Member reſpectively; and upon all and ſingular Land-rents and Inheritances whatſoever, within any ſuch Antient Town and any ſuch Member, and the Bounds, Limits, and Precincts belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſame reſpectively; as alſo upon all and ſingular the Goods, Chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels, and Merchandiſes of all and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular the Inhabitants or Reſiants, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:32072:55"/> Poſſeſſors or Tenants of any ſuch Lands or Inheritances whatſoever, within every ſuch Antient Town, and every ſuch Member, and the Bounds, Limits, and Precincts belonging to any one of them; and every Bayliff, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats, and Commons; and Bayliff, and Commons of every Member of the Ports aforeſaid where ſuch Bayliff is choſen by the Commons of the ſaid Member reſpectively, may in and upon themſelves and any other Inhabitants and Reſiants whatſoever, within every ſuch Member, Bounds, Limits, and Precincts of the ſame; and in and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all and ſingular the Land-rents, and Inheritances whatſoever, within every ſuch Member, and the Bounds, Limits, and Precincts belonging to every ſuch Member reſpectively; as alſo they may in and upon all and ſingular the Goods, Chattels, and Merchandiſes of all and ſingular the Inhabitants, whether Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors or Tenants of any ſuch Lands or Inheritances whatſoever within eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuch Member, and the Bounds, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, and Precincts of the ſame reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, ſet, aſſeſs, and lay from time to time as often as it ſhall ſeem neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to them, the Reaſonable and Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:32072:56"/> Taxes of Scot, Shot and Lot, Tallage, and the Reaſonable Taxes commonly called Common Fines,<note place="margin">Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Fines.</note> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſts, and Sums of Money to be paid within certain times or time to that purpoſe by them reſpectively limited and appointed; and by the ſame to be taken and levied upon the Inhabitants and Reſiants aforeſaid, or upon their Goods, Chattels, and Merchandiſes, Land-rents, Tenements, and Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances aforeſaid reſpectively, by the diſtraint and ſale of the ſame,<note place="margin">By the ſale.</note> or the impriſonment of the Bodies of the Perſons aforeſaid and every of them, upon whom ſuch Taxes of Scot, Lot, Shot,<note place="margin">As by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Bodies.</note> Tallage, Taxes called Common Fines, Impoſts, and Sums of Money, as is abovementioned, may or ſhall be put, laid, or aſſeſſed; Or which otherwiſe may be proſecuted by an Action or Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Debt in any Court of Record of the aforeſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> or Antient Towns aforeſaid, or Members of the ſame againſt any ſuch Perſon or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons reſpectively; Or may be recovered and obtained by any other legal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding whatſoever, as it ſhall ſeem beſt to them; and may be had, held, and enjoyed without any impediment of Us,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:32072:56"/> Our Heirs or Succeſſors Juſtices, or of any other the Miniſters of Us, Our Heirs or Succeſſors whatſoever; and all and ſingular the Premiſes afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid by theſe Preſents above granted or confirmed, or mentioned to be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after granted and confirmed to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Barons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> and Antient Towns and Members of the ſame Ports and Towns, and to their Succeſſors; and to the aforeſaid Mayor, Jurats, and Commons; Bayliff, Jurats, and Commons; and Bayliff and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the ſame <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, and Members of the ſame, and to their Succeſſors reſpectively for ever; For the payment and performance of ſo many, ſo great, the ſame and ſuch like Feofarms, Services, Rents, Sums of Tribute-pence, and demands whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever to Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, as many, as great, ſuch, and which as are or heretofore were due, accuſtomed, and payable to Us or Our Predeceſſors: Wherefore We Will, and by theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents firmly enjoyning, do Command for Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, That the aforeſaid Barons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> and Antient Towns, and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the ſame, and their Succeſſors,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:32072:57"/> and every of them and their Succeſſors; As alſo that the Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>Haſting</hi> aforeſaid, and their Succeſſors; as alſo the Mayor, Jurats, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the Town and Port of <hi>New-Romney</hi> aforeſaid, and their Succeſſors; as alſo the Mayor, Jurats, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the Town and Port of <hi>Heeth</hi> aforeſaid, and their Succeſſors; as alſo the Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>Dover</hi> aforeſaid, and their Succeſſors; and alſo the May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Port of <hi>Sandwich</hi> aforeſaid, and their Succeſſors; and alſo the Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Antient Town of <hi>Rye,</hi> and their Succeſſors; and alſo the Mayor, Jurats, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the Antient Town of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelſea,</hi> and their Succeſſors; and alſo the Bayliff, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Priviledged Monaſtery of <hi>Pevenſey</hi> aforeſaid, and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors; and alſo the Bayliff, Jurats, and Commons of the Town of <hi>Seaford</hi> aforeſaid, and their Succeſſors; as alſo the Bayliff, Jurats, and Commons of the Town of <hi>Lydd</hi> aforeſaid, and their Succeſſors; and alſo the Mayor, Jurats,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:32072:57"/> and Commons of the Town of Folk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone aforeſaid, and their Succeſſors; and alſo the Mayor, Jurats, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the Town of <hi>Feverſham</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and their Succeſſors; and alſo the Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town of <hi>Fordwich</hi> aforeſaid, and their Succeſſors; and alſo the Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Town and Hundred of <hi>Tenterden</hi> aforeſaid, and their Succeſſors, and every of them and their Succeſſors reſpectively have, hold, uſe, and enjoy, and may for ever have, hold, uſe, and enjoy all and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular the Liberties, Authorities, Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, Eranchiſes, Acquitances, Lands, Tents, Fairs, Marts, Markets, freedom from Toll and Tribute, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, and Priviledges aforeſaid accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Form and Tenor of theſe Our Letters Patents, and other Grants made to them, without any Action or impediment of Us,<note place="margin">Without the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> Our Heirs or Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, Juſtices, Sheriffs, Eſcheators, or other Bayliffs or Miniſters of Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors whatſoever: Nor Will We that they or their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors or any of them by reaſon of their Liberties or Immunities aforeſaid,<note place="margin">We will not.</note> be proſecuted, moleſted, vexed, or
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:32072:58"/> grieved, accuſed, or be in any thing troubled by any Action of Us, or Our Heirs, Juſtices, Sheriffs, Eſcheators, or other Bayliffs or Miniſters of Us, Our Heirs or Succeſſors whoſoever: We will and by theſe Preſents Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and Charge as well Our Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer, Chancellor, and Barons of Our Exchequer at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and the other Juſtices of Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, as Our Attorney and Sollicitor General for the time being,<note place="margin">Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and Sollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to the King.</note> and every of them, and all other Our Officers and Miniſters whoſoever, That neither they nor any of them ſhall proſecute or continue, or cauſe or make to be proſecuted or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued any Writ or Summons of <hi>Quo Warranto,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Quo War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranto.</note> or any other Writ or Writs, or Proceſs whatſoever in Our Name, againſt them or any of them for any Reaſons, Accounts, Matters, Claims, or Offences aforeſaid, or againſt any one or more of them reſpectively for any ſuch things which were due, claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, attempted, uſed, had, or uſurped in the time of the late Rebellion, and Revolting from the King, or at any other time before the making of theſe Preſents:<note place="margin">We will.</note> We Willing alſo that they or their Succeſſors or any of them be
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:32072:58"/> in no wiſe hindred or moleſted, or be compelled to anſwer for any ſuch thing or things, by any of the Juſtices, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, or Miniſters of Us, Our Heirs or Succeſſors, in or for any due, uſe, claim, or abuſe of any of the Liberties, Franchiſes, or Juriſdictions aforeſaid in the time of the Rebellion and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volting aforeſaid, or at any other time before the day of the making of theſe Our Letters Patents: Provided always, and Our Royal intent is, That theſe Our Letters Patents, or any thing therein contained be not in any wiſe prejudicial to the Warden or Keeper for the time being of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, and Members of the ſame, as to any Juriſdictions, Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, Liberties, or Priviledges within the aforeſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, and Members of the ſame, hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto lawfully uſed and exerciſed by the ſaid Wardens or Keepers of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, and Members of the ſame: Provided alſo, That theſe Letters Patents, or any thing or things contained or men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the ſame may in no wiſe extend or be extended to the confirming, ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening, eſtabliſhing, approving, or
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:32072:59"/> ratifying certain Letters Patents, or any thing or things in the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained or mentioned, made by the Lord <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth, late King of <hi>England,</hi> under his great Seat of <hi>England</hi> bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Date the Twenty eighth day of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> in the Five and twentieth year of his Reign, unto the Mayor of the Town of <hi>Feverſham,</hi> and to the Barons and Commons of the ſame Town, and their Succeſſors; Or heretofore made or granted, or mentioned to be granted under the Name of any other Incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration whatſoever; Nor to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming, ſtrengthening, eſtabliſhing, approving, or ratifying any Liberties, Franchiſes, Immunities, Priviledges, Exemptions, Grants, thing or things whatſoever given, granted, confirmed, contained, ſpecified or mentioned in the ſame Letters-Patents of the ſaid late King <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth; Nor to the confirming any other Letters Patents whatſoever concerning the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſtrengthning, or approving of the aforeſaid Letters Patents of the ſaid late King <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth, or of any thing or things contained or mentioned in the ſame Letters Patents of the ſaid late <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth, any thing in thoſe
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:32072:59"/> Patents to the contrariwiſe notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: And We further Will,<note place="margin">We will further.</note> and by theſe Preſents do Ordain, and ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enjoyning, do Command for Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, That all every May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, Bayliff, Jurat, Recorder, Coroner, Common Clerk, Conſtable, and all other Officers and Miniſters of the aforeſaid <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, and Members of the ſame, or any of them reſpectively, and their Deputies; as alſo that all Juſtices of Peace to Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, within the ſame <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, or Members of the ſame, or any one or more of them, by the virtue and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Tenour of theſe our Letters Patents, or of any other Letters Patents, or Charters heretofore made, who are now appointed, or hereafter are to be nominated, choſen, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, before they be admitted to the performance or exerciſe of the Office or Offices of the Place or Places to which they have been reſpectively ſo nominat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, appointed, elected, or ordained, or ſhall hereafter be nominated, elected, or ordained, or before that they or any of them reſpectively in any wiſe enter upon ſuch Place, they and every of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:32072:60" rendition="simple:additions"/> them ſhall take as well the Corporal Oath commonly called, <hi>The Oath of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> as the Corporal Oath commonly called, <hi>The Oath of Supremacy,</hi> upon the Sacred Goſpels of God, before ſuch Perſon or Perſons, as and which are at preſent, or ſhall be for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture appointed and deſigned to give and tender ſuch like Oaths by the Law and Statute of this Our Kingdom of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> And We further Will, and by theſe Preſents do Ordain and Declare for Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, That when any election for the future ſhall be made of any Perſon or Perſons who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever into the Office of a Recorder, or into the Office of a Town Clerk to any of the Ports, Towns, Members, or Places aforeſaid, otherwiſe than of ſuch and ſuch-like Perſon and Perſons who are now choſen and preferr'd in ſuch-like Office or Offices, and do now ſerve in the ſame or either of them reſpectively, if ſo be that We, Our Heirs or Succeſſors by any Writing or Warrant under the Hand and Seal of Us, Our Heirs or Succeſſors ſhall declare or ſignifie to the Barons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> aforeſaid, or to the Mayor, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats, and Commons; or to the Bayliff,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:32072:60" rendition="simple:additions"/> Jurats, and Commons; or to the Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff and Commons of the Ports and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Towns aforeſaid, and their Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, or to any other Officers and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of thoſe Ports and Towns, and the Members of the ſame reſpectively, to which ſuch Election or Elections re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively do belong to be made; Our or Our Heirs and Succeſſors diſallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch Perſon or Perſons reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively ſo elected to ſerve in ſuch like Office or Offices to which, as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, he or they were elected reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, That then and ſo often both by and after ſuch declaration and ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation made in the form aforeſaid, the Election or Elections of ſuch Perſon or Perſons ſo diſallowed as is aboveſaid, ſhall be void and of none effect: And that from that time it may and ſhall be lawful for the Barons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> aforeſaid, and the Members of the ſame; or for the Mayor, Jurats, and Commons of the Ports and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Towns aforeſaid, and of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the ſame; or for the Bayliff, Jurats, and Commons; or for the Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff and Commons of thoſe Ports and Towns, and the Members of the ſame, or any one or more of them reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:32072:61"/> to whom ſuch Election or Elections reſpectively belong to be made, to chuſe, nominate, and Swear any other honeſt and diſcreet Perſon or Perſons, fit for the executing the Office or Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices aforeſaid unto which he or they ſhall be reſpectively nominated and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected into the Place or Places of ſuch Perſon or Perſons, ſo, as is aforeſaid, elected and afterwards diſallowed; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Tenor of theſe Preſents, and other Letters Patents and Grants of any of Our Predeceſſors made for that purpoſe: And thus as often as ſuch a Caſe ſhall happen, (any thing contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in theſe Preſents, or any other reaſon, cauſe, or matter whatſoever to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.) And that expeſs mention is not made in theſe Preſents of the true yearly value, or of the certainty of the Premiſes or of any of them, or of other Gifts or Grants heretofore made by Us, or by any of our Progenitors or Predeceſſors to the aforeſaid Barons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> and to the Mayor, Jurats, and Commons; to the Bayliff, Jurats, and Commons; and to the Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff and Jurats of the ſame <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> Antient Towns, and Members of the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:32072:61"/> ſame, and to their Succeſſors; Or any Act, Ordinance, Proviſo, Proclamation, or Reſtraint to the contrary heretofore had, made, publiſhed, ordained, or provided, or any other reaſon, cauſe, or matter whatſoever in any thing not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding. In Witneſs whereof, We have cauſed theſe Our Letters to be made Patents.</p>
               <p>Witneſs Our Self at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the Three and twentieth day of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> in the Twentieth Year of the Reign of Us <hi>Charles</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By a Writ of the Privy Seal.</hi> Pigott.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="122" facs="tcp:32072:62"/>
            <head>The Doquet.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THIs contains Your Majeſties Grant and Confirmation unto the Barons of the <hi>Cinque-Ports,</hi> and to the Towns and Members of the ſame, of their Ancient Charters, Liberties, and Priviledges, and of ſome Particulars formerly granted, and hereby renewed in regard of ſome ſmall Defects therein; and with power to make Deputies, and recover the things granted by Actions of Debt: Alſo a Proviſion for all Officers to take the Oaths of Obedience and Supremacy, and a Reſervation of Power to Your Majeſty to put out any Recorder, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Town-Clerk hereafter to be choſen, (othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> than thoſe now in place) or any ſignification of Your Majeſties Diſlike, under Your Sig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Manual; and with ſuch other Clauſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are uſual in Grants of like nature.</p>
            <byline>By Sign Manual.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="glossary">
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:32072:62"/>
            <head>An Explication by way of Alphabet of all the hard and obſolete Words that are to be found in the foregoing Charter.</head>
            <div n="A" type="part">
               <head>A.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AChatum Reachatum</hi> are uſed for a Contract or Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain by way of Buying and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buying, Selling and Re-ſelling.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aponſagium,</hi> Bridgtoll, <hi>vid, <hi>Pontagium.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ambiderter,</hi> is he, that when a Matter is in Suit betwixt any, taketh Money of one ſide and of the other to plead for the Suit or ſuch like,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:32072:63"/> or if he be a Jury-Man, to ſay his verdict.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Attaint,</hi> is a Writ, and lieth where falſe Verdict is given by Twelve Men, and Judgment given thereon, then the Party againſt whom they have paſſed, ſhall have a Writ againſt the Twelve Men, and when they be at Iſſue, it ſhall be Tried by Twenty four Jury Men, and if the falſe Verdict be found, the Twelve Men be Attaint, and then the Judgment ſhall be, That their Meadows ſhall be eyred, their Houſes broken down, their Woods turned up, and all their Lands and Tenements forfeited to the King: but if it paſs againſt him that brought that Attaint, he ſhall be impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and grievouſly Ranſomed at the Kings Will.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aſſiſe,</hi> is taken for a Writ di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to the Sheriff for the reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of things immovable, whereof your ſelf, or your Anceſtor hath been Diſſeiſed.</p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:32072:63"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aſſiſe,</hi> of <hi>Novel Diſſeiſin,</hi> lieth where a Tenant in Fee-Simple, Fee-Tail, or for Term of Life, is lately Diſſeiſed of his Lands or Tenements, or elſe of a Rent-Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, Rent-Seck, or Rent-Charge, of Common of Paſture, of an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, of Toll, Tronage, Paſſage, Pawnage, or for a Nuiſance levied, and divers other ſuch like.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aſſiſe</hi> of <hi>Mort d' Anceſter,</hi> lieth where my Father, Mother, Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Siſter, Uncle, Aunt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> died ſeiſed of Lands, Tenements, Rents, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that he had in Fee-Simple, and after his Death a Stranger abat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: and it is as good, as well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Abator, as any other in Poſſeſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aſſiſe</hi> of <hi>Rediſſeiſin,</hi> is where a Man is Diſſeiſed, and recovereth by <hi>Aſſiſe</hi> of <hi>Novel Diſſeiſin,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward is again Diſſeiſed by the ſame Diſſeiſor, he ſhall have againſt him a Writ of <hi>Diſſeiſin</hi> directed to the Sheriff to make Inquiſition, and
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:32072:64"/> if the <hi>Rediſſeiſin</hi> be found, he ſhall be ſent to Priſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="B" type="part">
               <head>B.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brevis, <hi>(Briefe)</hi>
                  </hi> ſignifies moſt properly in our Law, the Proceſs that iſſues out of the <hi>Chancery</hi> or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Courts, Commanding the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riff to Summon or Attach <hi>A.</hi> to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer <hi>B.</hi> But more largely it is taken for any Precept of the King in Writing under Seal, iſſuing out of any Court, whereby he Commands any thing to be done, for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of Juſtice, and good Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. In <hi>Engliſh,</hi> a Writ.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="C" type="part">
               <head>C.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Champartie,</hi> or Bribe, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth in the Common Law, a main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of any Man in his Suit de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending, upon condition to have part
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:32072:64"/> of the thing (be it Lands or Goods) when it is recovered.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Champertours,</hi> be they, that move Pleas or Suits, or cauſe to be moved, either by their own procure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or by other; and purſue at their proper Coſts, for to have part of the Land in variance, or part of the Gains.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Common Fines,</hi> are a certain Sum of Money, which the Reſiants of a Court Leet pay to the Lord of the Leet, towards his Charge of Purchaſing the Leet.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="D" type="part">
               <head>D.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Den. &amp; Strond,</hi> the former whereof ſignifies an hollow place to put things in; the latter, the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhore.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doquet,</hi> or <hi>Docket,</hi> is a little piece of Paper or Parchment written, that containeth in it the effect of a greater Writing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="E" type="part">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:32072:65"/>
               <head>E.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eſcheat,</hi> is where a Tenant in Fee-Simple doth Felony, for the which he is Hanged or Abjured the Realm, or be Outlawed for Felony, Murder, or Petty-Treaſon; or if the Tenant dye without Heirs ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral or ſpecial, then the Lord of whom the Tenant held the Land may enter by way of <hi>Eſcheat,</hi> or if any other enter, the Lord ſhall have againſt him a Writ, called a Writ of <hi>Eſcheat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eſcheator,</hi> is an Officer who obſerves ſuch <hi>Eſcheats</hi> which belong to the King, and Certifieth them into the Eſchequer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eſtray,</hi> is where any Beaſt or Cattel are in a Lordſhip, and none knoweth the Owner thereof, then it ſhall be ſeized to the uſe of the King, or of the Lord that hath ſuch <hi>Eſtray</hi> by the Kings Grant, or by
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:32072:65"/> Preſcription: and if the Owner come and make Claim thereto within a year and a day, then he ſhall have it again, or elſe after the year the Propriety thereof ſhall be to the Lord, ſo that the Lord make Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation thereof according to the Law.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eſcape,</hi> is where one that is Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted comes to his Liberty, before he be delivered by award of Juſtice, or by order of Law.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exigent,</hi> is a Writ that lieth where the Defendant in Action Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal cannot be found, nor any thing within the County whereby to be Attached or Diſtreined, and is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to the Sheriff to make Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation at five Counties one after another, that he appear, or elſe that he ſhall be Outlawed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="F" type="part">
               <head>F.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Foreſtall,</hi> is to be quit of Amerce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:32072:66"/> and Cattels Arreſted within your Land, and the Amercements thereof coming.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Foreſtaller,</hi> is he that Buyeth Corn, Cattel, or other Merchandize, whatſoever is Saleable by the way as it cometh to Markets, Fairs, or ſuch like Places to be Sold, to the intent that he may Sell the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain at a more high and dear Price, in Prejudice and Hurt of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Wealth and People.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="G" type="part">
               <head>G.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gild,</hi> hath divers ſignifications, as ſometimes a Tribute, other times an Amercement, thirdly a Frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity or Company combined together by Orders and Laws made amongſt themſelves by the Kings Licenſe, fourthly 'tis uſed for a Preſtation within the Foreſt to be made for gathering of Sheaves of Corn, of Lamb, and of Wool to the uſe of the Foreſters.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="H" type="part">
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:32072:66"/>
               <head>H.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hidage,</hi> is to be quit, if the King ſhall Tax all the Land by Hides; now an Hide is a whole Plough-Land.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hoſtellar,</hi> is an Inn-Keeper.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="I" type="part">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Infangtheff,</hi> is, that Thieves taken within your Demeſne or Fee Convicted of Theft, ſhall be Judged in your Court.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ingroſſer,</hi> is one that Buyeth Corn, Grain, Butter, Cheeſe, Fiſh, or other dead Victuals, with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to ſell the ſame again at a higher and deerer Price. <hi>Regrator</hi> is the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="K" type="part">
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:32072:67"/>
               <head>K.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Kiage,</hi> is a Toll required for Keys and Wharfs by the Water ſide; or rather the Cuſtom paid for Whar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fage, or loading aid unloading Goods.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="L" type="part">
               <head>L.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtage,</hi> is a Cuſtom challenged in Fairs and Markets for carrying of things where a Man will. <hi>Laſtage-Free,</hi> is to be exempt from that Cuſtom.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtis</hi> Hundred, is a bigger ſort of Hundred containing about three ordinary ones; <hi>Sandwich</hi> in <hi>Kent</hi> is ſo called.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lot</hi> and <hi>Scot,</hi> ſignifie a Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary Contribution laid upon all Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects according to their ability.</p>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:32072:67"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lovecopefree,</hi> this Word is not to be explained, or elſe it is falſe Printed for <hi>Lot</hi> and <hi>Copefree:</hi> now <hi>Copefree</hi> is to be quit from Poll-Money; Or elſe it ſignifies to be quit from that which Diggers of Mines pay to the Lord for breaking up his Ground.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="M" type="part">
               <head>M.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mariage,</hi> ſignifieth not only the coupling together of Man and Wife, but alſo the beſtowing a Ward or a Widow in Mariage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Manutenentiae,</hi> Maintenance, in our Common Law is uſed in the evil part, for him, that ſecondeth a Cauſe depending in Suit between others, either by lending of Money, or making Friends for either Party, toward his help; then the injured Party may have againſt him a Writ of <hi>Maintenance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Miſericordia,</hi> is uſed in the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:32072:68"/> Common Law for an Amercement or Mulct ſet upon any for Offence; ſo that if a Man be outragiouſly A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merced in a Court that is not of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, as in a Court Baron, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> there is a Writ called a <hi>Moderata Miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia</hi> to be directed to the Lord or his Baily, Commanding them that they take moderate Amercements according to the quantity of the fault.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Murage,</hi> is a Toll levied for the Building or Repairing of Publick Walls; it ſeemeth alſo to be a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty granted by the King to a Town, for the gathering of Money toward Walling of the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="N" type="part">
               <head>N.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Novel Diſſeiſin.</hi> See before, <hi>Aſſiſe</hi> of <hi>Novel Diſſeiſin.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="O" type="part">
               <head>O.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Outfangtheff, <hi>alias <hi>Ufang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theff,</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </hi> is, that Thieves or Felons of
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:32072:68"/> your Land or Fee, out of your Land or Fee, taken with Felony or Steal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſhall be brought back to your Court and there judged.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="P" type="part">
               <head>P.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paſſage,</hi> ſignifies the Hire that a Man payeth, for being tranſported Over-Sea.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pannage,</hi> or <hi>Pawnage,</hi> is that Money which the Agiſtors of Foreſts do gather for the feeding of Hogs within the Foreſt; and it is alſo taken for all manner of Maſt-Trees within the Foreſt, on which the Hogs do feed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pontage,</hi> is either the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution which is gathered, or the Toll which is paid by Paſſengers for the Repair of Bridges; it is called alſo <hi>Brigbote.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peiſage,</hi> is Weight and Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: from <hi>Peiſa,</hi> ſignifieth Weight.</p>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:32072:69"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Piccage,</hi> is the Money paid for the breaking of the Ground to ſet up Booths and Standings in Fairs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="Q" type="part">
               <head>Q.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quietancia, <hi>alias <hi>Acquietan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia,</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </hi> is a Releaſe or Diſcharge from any Debt formerly due.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quo Warranto,</hi> is a Writ which lieth againſt him that Uſurps any Franchiſe from the King, then the King ſhall have this Writ to make him come before his Juſtices, and ſhew what Warrant or Title he hath to demand ſuch Franchiſe: Or elſe it ſignifieth a Writ againſt him that intrudeth himſelf as Heir into Land.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="R" type="part">
               <head>R.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Riverage,</hi> is that which is paid for being carried over a River.</p>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:32072:69"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Right Priſage</hi> of Wines, is a Cuſtom whereby the King challeng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out of every Bark loaden with Wine, containing leſs than forty Tun, two Tun of Wine at his own Price.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Regrator;</hi> See, <hi>Ingroſſer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rediſſeiſin;</hi> See, <hi>Aſſiſe</hi> of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſeiſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Recordate,</hi> is a Writ directed to the Sheriff, to remove a Cauſe out of an inferior Court, into the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> or <hi>Common-Pleas.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="S" type="part">
               <head>S.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Soc,</hi> is a liberty or power to ſeek after Thieves or Stolen Goods, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a Mannor, and to do juſtice upon the Inquiſition: It is alſo taken for the Company of Tenents which live within ſuch a Liberty, and are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from thoſe common Services of the Prince and Countrey where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto Subjects are ordinarily tied.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sac,</hi> is a Royalty or Priviledge touching Plea and Correction of
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:32072:70"/> Treſpaſſes within a Mannor, and to have the Amercements of ones Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants in ones own Court.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stallage,</hi> is a certain Cuſtom exacted for the Street taken or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned in Fairs and Markets.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scot,</hi> See, <hi>Lot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shot,</hi> is Tax-Money.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scutage,</hi> Eſcuage, or a kind of Knights-Service, called Service of the Shield, whereby a Tenant who holds by Knight-Service, is bound to follow his Lord into the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> or <hi>Welſh</hi> Wars, at his own charge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Strip,</hi> or <hi>Eſtrepement,</hi> is a Writ for taking Lands from him that ſtrips and ſpoils them: Or properly, the unmeaſurable ſoaking or drawing of the heart of the Land by Plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or Sowing it continually, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Manuring, or other ſuch uſeage as is requiſite in good Husbandry.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="T" type="part">
               <head>T.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tallage,</hi> is uſed for the ſhare of a Mans Subſtance paid by way of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute.</p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:32072:70"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theolonium Tolnetum,</hi> Toll or Cuſtom paid to the King.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thol,</hi> is the liberty of Buying and Selling in ones own Ground.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Them,</hi> is the Priviledge of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Generations of your Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains, with their Suits and Cattel, whereſoever they ſhall be found in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Terrage,</hi> is a freeing from Land-Taxes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tumbrel,</hi> is a Cucking-Stool, a Puniſhment for Scolds.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="V" type="part">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>View</hi> of <hi>Frankpledge,</hi> is a Writ to exempt one from the <hi>View</hi> of <hi>Frankpledge,</hi> who is not Reſident within the Hundred: <hi>Frankpledge</hi> is a Cuſtom whereby Neighbours were commonly bound one for another, to be Sureties for each others Truth to the King and his Subjects.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vtlagat,</hi> is an Out-lawed Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:32072:71"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vetit-Mamium,</hi> a Writ of <hi>Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thernam,</hi> which is directed to the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riff for the taking as many of the Mans Goods who did Diſtrein un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully from another, as the value of the Diſtreined Goods comes to: And if the Goods or Beaſts be in a Fortlet or Caſtle, the Sheriff may take with him the Power of the County, and beat down the Caſtle.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="W" type="part">
               <head>W.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Waſt,</hi> is when a Tenant lets the Houſe fall, or pulls it down, or cuts down any thing with damage to the Land that he poſſeſſeth: It is alſo a Puniſhment or Forfeiture belonging to Petit-Treaſon or Felony.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wret,</hi> is where a Ship is periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Sea, and no Man eſcapeth alive out of the ſame, and the Ship or part of the Ship ſo periſhed, or the Goods of the Ship come to the Land of any Lord, the Lord ſhall have that as a Wreck of the Sea. But if a Man, or a Dog, or a Cat, eſcape alive, ſo that the Party to
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:32072:71"/> whom the Goods belong, come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a year and a day, and prove the Goods to be his, he ſhall have them again.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Witfree,</hi> is a Diſcharge from all Defaults and Amercements.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Waviat,</hi> is when Goods are ſeized by Waif, which is the Goods of a Thief, whether ſtolen or not, which upon urgent neceſſity, as haſte, or ſuch like, he hath left any where behind him, then the Kings Officer, or the Bayliff to the Lord within whoſe Juriſdiction they were left, who by Preſcription or Grant from the King hath the Franchiſe of <hi>Waif,</hi> may ſeize the Goods ſo Waived to to the Lords uſe, who may keep them as his own, unleſs the Owner come and lay claim to them, within a year and a day.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
